<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Vox vera: or, Obseruations from Amsterdam Examining the late insolencies of some pseudo-puritans, separatists from the Church of Great Brittaine. And closed vp with a serious three-fold aduertisement for the generall vse of euery good subiect within his Maiesties dominions, but more especially of those in the kingdome of Scotland. By Patricke Scot, North-Brittaine.</title>
            <author>Scot, Patrick.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 121 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11621</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21863</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116886</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852101</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852101</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17407</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11621)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17407)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1256:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Vox vera: or, Obseruations from Amsterdam Examining the late insolencies of some pseudo-puritans, separatists from the Church of Great Brittaine. And closed vp with a serious three-fold aduertisement for the generall vse of euery good subiect within his Maiesties dominions, but more especially of those in the kingdome of Scotland. By Patricke Scot, North-Brittaine.</title>
                  <author>Scot, Patrick.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 62 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Bernard Alsop,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In part a reply to: Calderwood, David.  The altar of Damascus.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Calderwood, David, 1575-1650. --  Altar of Damascus --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of Scotland --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Puritans --  Amsterdam (Netherlands) --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17407:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17407:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>VOX VERA: OR, OBSERVATIONS FROM AMSTERDAM. <hi>Examining</hi> The late Inſolencies of ſome PSEVDO-PVRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TANS, Separatiſts from the Church of GREAT BRITTAINE. And Cloſed vp with a ſerious three-fold Aduertiſement for the generall vſe of euery good Subiect within his Maieſties Dominions, but more eſpecially of thoſe in the Kingdome of SCOTLAND.</p>
            <p>By PATRICKE SCOT, <hi>North-Brittaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>STOB. SERM. 44.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Quae naſcentia mala ſunt, ea creſcentia peiora.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by BERNARD ALSOP. 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:17407:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17407:2"/>
            <head>OT THE GENE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ROVS READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F (as is wittily mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized) infants at their firſt entry into the world, bewaile the fall of our firſt <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents;</hi> I finde no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why thoſe that are of full age may not <hi>vera voce, condole</hi> either priuate <hi>diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers</hi> or <hi>publike calamities;</hi> or that I ſhould not publiſh this <hi>abortiue birth,</hi> expoſtulating a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe <hi>Empiricks</hi> and <hi>firebrands,</hi> that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to enflame the <hi>Church,</hi> and incenſe the <hi>ſtate,</hi> that thereby a <hi>pluriſie</hi> of <hi>troubles</hi> and generall <hi>combuſtion</hi> might enſue indange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the peace of the one, or troubling the calme of other.</p>
            <p>As my <hi>ſtile</hi> is <hi>dull,</hi> plaine without <hi>affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> rather to deliuer <hi>trueth</hi> then ſhew <hi>art:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17407:3"/> ſo are my <hi>aimes ſincere</hi> and <hi>free</hi> of all <hi>ſquint-eyed</hi> inducements.</p>
            <p>My dutie to the <hi>Church, allegeance</hi> to my <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> and danger of <hi>ſchiſmaticall praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents</hi> are the <hi>fires</hi> that haue tempered this <hi>Telamonian ſhield,</hi> vnder whoſe ſhelter this <hi>Shepheard-like ſubiect</hi> oppoſeth the naked ſimplicitie of <hi>trueth</hi> againſt the enraged <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liahs</hi> of this <hi>age,</hi> armed with gliſtring ſhows of fineſt <hi>forgery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One fauour I craue, that thy <hi>miſpriſion</hi> wrong me not, as if I did not diſtinguiſh ſuch <hi>graue, ſober,</hi> and peaceable <hi>ſpirits</hi> in the <hi>Clergie</hi> or <hi>Laitie,</hi> at home or abroad, that (though different in opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſome points of externall diſcipline and <hi>policie</hi>) containe themſelues within the <hi>precinct</hi> of that vnity and modeſty preſcribed by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> in like caſes.</p>
            <p>As I eſteeme it <hi>ſacriledge</hi> to detract from the leaſt deſert of any ſober <hi>Chriſtian:</hi> ſo hold I it <hi>Religion</hi> to vnmaske the <hi>viperous brood</hi> of <hi>Parricidos,</hi> whoſe inuenomed <hi>ſhafts</hi> I paſſe by with contempt, neglecting whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch <hi>dogs barke, ſnarle</hi> or <hi>fawne. Dum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiae ſatisfacio nihil in famam laboro ſequatur
<pb facs="tcp:17407:3"/> vel mala dum bene mereor;</hi> darke <hi>ſhadowes</hi> doe no leſſe attend beautifull then deformed <hi>bodies,</hi> in brighteſt <hi>Sunſhine.</hi> If I ſhould labor other ſatisfaction, it were an effect of <hi>frenzy</hi> not of <hi>hope,</hi> ſince it is no <hi>trueth</hi> but <hi>opinion</hi> which trauelleth the <hi>Coaſts</hi> without <hi>paſport,</hi> that I am to ſuruey.</p>
            <p>If thou read iudiciouſly without partiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty I expect thy fauorable <hi>cenſure</hi> of this <hi>task,</hi> meditated whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the raging <hi>waues</hi> of ſtormy <hi>Seas</hi> incenſed with <hi>thundring winds,</hi> aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>deaths pale colours</hi> to the terrour as well of <hi>Mariners</hi> as <hi>Paſſengers;</hi> penned after my ſafe expoſall vpon a forraigne <hi>ſhore,</hi> when the ſad reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of ſome of my friends &amp; familiars lately ſunke into the <hi>vnſatiable belly</hi> of the vaſt <hi>Ocean,</hi> much diſtempered my <hi>braine,</hi> and confuſed my <hi>memory;</hi> now publiſhed to the praiſe of that <hi>ſupreame Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie,</hi> by whoſe grace I hope hereafter, in a more calme aire, to erect a thankfull <hi>memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall</hi> of ſo great a deliuery. <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>P. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17407:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17407:4"/>
            <head>VOX VERA.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the humour of <hi>ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſeditious,</hi> and <hi>ſciſmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall</hi> ſpirits, in the entry of their deſignes to ſtudie po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pularitie,<note place="margin">Fauor in apud Stob.</note> and being drunke with vulgar applauſe, the vaine glory thereof raiſeth their conceits many ſtrains higher then really they are: as if Greatneſſe and Wiſdome ingrauen in their forehead by open force, or ſubtill perſwaſion, might ſurprize both enemies and friends,<note place="margin">Lact. lib. 3. Philoſt.</note> when in true por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traiture they reſemble the rearers vp of Babel, the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that moſt torment the world, and that <hi>Cerberus</hi> that ſets open hell gates, to let looſe ſuch ſpirits as fill the world with impoſture, in this period, or rather dregs of decaying time,<note place="margin">2. Tim. cap. 3. v. 2.3.4.5.</note> wherein the imperious nature of domination in irregular minds cannot indure limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, but muſt, and will, range abroad in the wide wilde-field of humours, and draw attentiue Auditors to the Prologue of ſuch Tragedies as are embelliſhed with ſhowes of great matters; or rather falſe hopes to conquer the world with the Sword of the Spirit: as if all others were poſſeſſed with a Lethargie or Frenſie
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17407:5"/> (extreme diſeaſes that cannot bee cured with <hi>Manna</hi> and gentle remedies) and that ſuch <hi>Quackſaluers</hi> are onely the <hi>Phiſitians</hi> to cure the world ſo deadly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hiſtor. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</note>Thus from the beginning hath God left ſome rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants of Cananites to proue Iſrael by them, &amp; to teach them ware that did not know it before, thereby try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the faith and patience of his Church, which neuer wanteth <hi>Seminaries</hi> of <hi>Atheiſme,</hi> and brochers of lewd libertie, who vnder religious habit are the ſole e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to all religion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Floren. Schon.</note>
               <hi>Sub hoc mantili &amp; euerriculo multarum fraudum, fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>da ingenia violentiam naturae, aut profundam ambitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem velare ſtudent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The time allotted to theſe enſuing obſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhould run out,<note place="margin">The Induction</note> before I brought to the view of the Reader, the leaſt part of thoſe inſtances of this kind, wherwith both Churches and States haue been infected or poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned; all which I will leaue, and onely bring to the Stage ſome few of the moſt recent diſloyall practiſes, and ſelfe conceited <hi>ſciſmaticall opinions,</hi> of home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred <hi>phariſaicall hypocrites,</hi> that bluſh not to aſſume the face of an harlot, <hi>ſurrepticiouſly</hi> chalenge the title of the Church, &amp; ſend abroad ſuch poſitions, as labor to draw ſoueraigntie into contempt, annihilate iuſt lawes, taint ſuperiour powers with diſgracefull notes, and erect democracie or orderleſſe confuſion, in both Church and State, if the moſt deuouring ſtomach of ambition or ſingularitie, could ſwallow ſuch choking morſels before it come at them.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:17407:5"/>Ludit in humanis deuina potentia rebus.</q>
            <p>He that made the world, can make ſuch learn by their errors, <hi>Plus eſt in artifice quam in arte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Would to God I could ſaile by ſome other point of the <hi>Compaſſe,</hi> then by that which directeth my courſe againſt thoſe <hi>rockes of diuiſion,</hi> or <hi>ſinking ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes of diſloyaltie,</hi> whereupon it is likely, ſome Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts from the Church of great Britaine are already ſhip-broken; and that others, yet toſſed with ſciſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall ſtormes, are like to be caſt vpon the ſame Coaſt.</p>
            <p>Let it not then ſeeme ſtrange to the eye of preiudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate opinion, that the common obligation of euery good ſubiect, tieth me to expoſtulate againſt the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious forgeries of ſuch enemies to peace; as vncouer theſe Trophes of diſgrace, which they haue erected to tell their ſhame to poſteritie, and to ſound the depth of theſe riotous miſdemeanours, which in my late ſuruey of the <hi>vnited Prouinces,</hi> I haue ſeene, at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and other places; where diſperſing of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous <hi>Libels,</hi> might either curry fauour in the eye of licentious <hi>Libertines,</hi> malecontented <hi>Fugitiues,</hi> or profeſſed Enemies.</p>
            <p>There, I did behold, euery Bookeſellers ſhop, and moſt Pedlers ſtalles, loaden with the nullitie of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes</hi> aſſembly; the Altar of <hi>Damaſeus,</hi> the Dialogue betwixt <hi>Theophilus</hi> and <hi>Coſmophilus,</hi> the Speech of the Church of Scotland to her beloued Children, and the courſe of Conformitie ioyned with all theſe (ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerally printed before) reprinted in one volume, and to be ſold at no leſſe rate then if they had beene Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of <hi>Apollo.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:17407:6"/>
            <p>Secondly, did come to my hand the petition of the Kirke of <hi>Scotland</hi> to the heigh <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England</hi> a <hi>methodicall</hi> well digeſted <hi>peece</hi> beſeeming the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Church that did preferre it: next was offered to me, <hi>Speculum belli ſacri,</hi> or the mirrour of holy warre, a ſquint eyed worke looking at military inſtructions, but aiming at idle impetinent, impudent and fond ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, as if <hi>Giges</hi> ring had beene vpon the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours</hi> finger, or his whole body ſheltered when his head was not couered: next to my greater admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, did I behold <hi>Altare Damaſcenum, ſeu politia Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae Anglicanae obtruſa Eccleſiae Scoticanae à formaliſta quodam delineata opera Edwardi Didoclauii, cui locis ſuis inſerta confutatio Paraneſeos Tileni ad Scotos, cui adiuncta Epiſtola Philadelphi de regimine Ecleſiae Scoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canae per Anonimum.</hi> Theſe were cloſed vp a malicious Satiriſme againſt a learned graue Treatiſe written by the Archbiſhop of Saint <hi>Andrewes,</hi> whoſe integritie of life, and ſinceritie of <hi>Religion,</hi> none but barking curres can taxe.</p>
            <p>In all theſe trumpets of <hi>Sedition,</hi> whether in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh to enſnare <hi>domeſtike natiues,</hi> or in Latine to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade <hi>forraigne alients</hi> to their faction, <hi>ſacred ſcripture</hi> was neuer more ſenſibly corrupted, more wickedly wreſted, more impertinently applyed, neither was euer the ſacred perſon of <hi>Soueraigntie,</hi> the dignitie of the <hi>learned Clergie,</hi> the communion of Chriſtians and the loyaltie of good ſubiects more trampled vpon, by the moſt prophane <hi>Atheiſt</hi> or <hi>heretike,</hi> or by <hi>Sathan</hi> himſelfe then by theſe poyſonable <hi>Satiriſmes</hi> ouer-flowing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17407:6"/> with gall, and masked with prepoſterous zeale; in which mirrors of conſpiracy euery good ſubiect may obſerue, that if it were as eaſie to ſome of thoſe violent ſpirits, to bring their purpoſes to their ends, as it is to finde ſhadowes for their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, it is to be feared the fruites of their vnſanctified doctrine ſhould haue beene dyed in blood long ago, and warranted with <hi>ſic dicit Dominus</hi> A bloody di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſition is as well concomitant to <hi>ſciſmatikes</hi> as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt <hi>Atheiſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eraſm. in apo.</note> and where euer the quickſiluer of <hi>ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is ingredient, there the fire of contention is <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable,</hi> howſoeuer it may bee ſmothered for a time into aſhes of ſeeming holineſſe. <hi>Pirates</hi> haue their prayers as well as honeſt Merchants;<note place="margin">Fulgoſex. Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton. Dion. Nic.</note> 
               <hi>Geta</hi> in killing his brother <hi>Caracalla</hi> had his bloody Maske; when <hi>Sathan</hi> appeared to <hi>Saul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sa. 1.1.18.14.</note> hee was lapped in <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muels</hi> Mantle; <hi>Mahomet</hi> did abuſe the world with the name of the Angell <hi>Gabriel;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mai. 4.6.</note> the Tempter could alledge Scripture againſt <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe; and it is credibly reported, that an <hi>Amſterdam</hi> ſiſter did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encourage her owne daughter to periury by telling her, <hi>It is better to fall in the hands of God, then of man.</hi> Aske whatſoeuer ſciſmaticke the reaſon of their profeſſion, and they will anſwer, that the ſacred Scripture is the leuell whereby they ſquare the frame and infallibilitie of their ſeuerall Churches;<note place="margin">Knox ad No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilit. Scot. and in his hir of Scot. Good man vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the 17. of Exod.</note> why may not then <hi>Didoclauius, Philadelphus, Anonimus,</hi> or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther late <hi>Lybellers</hi> imitate ſuch preſidents, and peruert ſcriptures as wel as others; yet me thinkes it ſhould ſeem ſtrange in the eie of ſober iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that men pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17407:7"/> to haue the onely truth of religion ſhould equally proſecute their ſeditious deſignes without conſcience in contempt of authoritie, as they make <hi>Idols</hi> of their owne braine-ſicke conceptions againſt the rules of true wiſdom. When any of contrary opinion, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ordinance of the Church, ſtrengthened by ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill power, would louingly perſwade them to forbeare to walke in forbidden pathes, they cloſe their eares, or without weighing of reaſon, anſwer by the words of <hi>Iohn, We are of God, he that knoweth God heareth vs,</hi> as for the reſt, <hi>they are of the world &amp; the world whoſe pompe &amp; &amp; vanitie they follow heareth them:</hi> when the dignity of authoritie, and honour of Gods Magiſtrates is vphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den againſt them, or their inabilitie to iudge in the <hi>miſteries</hi> of <hi>State</hi> ſhewne them: they anſwer with the Anabaptiſt, <hi>God hath choſen the ſimple.</hi> Will you ſo ſenſibly conuince them of folly, that very children may vpbraid them of it, they will tell you that <hi>Chriſts owne Apoſtles were accounted mad.</hi> Selfe conceit and flatterie hath ſo tickled and ſcratched their ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der eares,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.3.</note> that they are impatient of the leaſt touch of rough truth. When admonition nor no faire means can preuaile, let them but feele the lighteſt dramme of iuſtice, they ſtreight lay vpon Gods vicegerents; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they any where finde againſt the crueltie of moſt blood thirſtie tyrants, drawing to themſelues all ſuch ſentences as Scripture hath for innocency per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted for righteouſneſſe, as if euery ſeditious diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of State that ſuffers for diſobedience and breach of Chriſtian vnitie might chalenge the name of a Martir.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:17407:7"/>
            <p>Theſe be the paths wherein <hi>ſeparation</hi> walketh, the ſteps it doth tread, the doctrine wherein it is trained vp in the ſchoole of faction and the toyles and toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of vnquiet ſpirits that are ſo diſtaſtfull to men of more peaceable temper, that if violence done to reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, vncharitable railing againſt <hi>Maieſtie</hi> and <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy,</hi> might be buried in ſilence, they would rather ſuffer millions of perſonall aſperſions, then interrupt the peace of the Church or quiet of the ſtate, by oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the ſiſmaticall practices of reſtleſſe braines, who like fiſhers in troubled waters, delight in commotions and tumults: <hi>Quam dignitatis ſedem quieta republica diſperant eam perturbata ſe conſequi poſſe arbitrantur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when the <hi>King</hi> which is the head, or the <hi>State</hi> which is the body, or <hi>Religion</hi> which is the <hi>ſoule</hi> of the commonwealth, are in queſtion to receiue preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice; neceſſitie, which is a law aboue all lawes, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies the place of an ordinary calling: then it is a harmefull modeſtie to keepe ſilence, or too late to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer ſuch <hi>ſulphurious mines</hi> when the match kiſſeth the powder. As when the ſhadow of mount <hi>Athos</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the Ile <hi>Lemnos,</hi> it is a ſure forerunner of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downe of the Sun, and time for ſhepheards to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pale their flockes: So when ſeditious confuſion ſtriues to ouer-reach both <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> it is time as wel to ſubiect as magiſtrate according to their ſeuerall places, to remoue ſuch fuell, leaſt the fire become vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable, and bring ruine on the one, and deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on the other. O miſerable times, <hi>vbi tacere non li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet quid cuiquam licet?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is it not a moſt arrogant preſumption, that humo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſts
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17407:8"/> vnder zealous pretexts ſhould preferre ſingular paradoxes of pride and contention, for euery circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of leaſt moment, to the feeding of their flockes, vpon the ſweet paſtors of <hi>humility, charity,</hi> and other Chriſtian duties? it is aboue admiration, that others ſhould glory more in their adherents to ſuch lying <hi>Oracles,</hi> then in their Chriſtian obedience inioyned or pietie profeſſed. Is there a more palpable errour then to receiue euery article of externall diſcipline with the like reuerence, honour them with the like re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, and defend them with the like tenacitie, as if they were matters of <hi>faith</hi> commanded by <hi>canonicall Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtles and ſacred writ haue deliuered vnto vs, no other precepts, concerning the externall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the Church, then that <hi>all things in the Church may be done decently and in order:</hi> But on the contrary,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 14.4.</note> our <hi>Didoclauius</hi> and his followers charge vs at no leſſe perill then our ſoules, that we marre all decency, ouerturne all order, by diſparaging the ſtate with contempt, and making that <hi>honourable Title</hi> of true <hi>Catholike</hi> euer lyable to ſcandall, if not to ſciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſo long as <hi>phantaſticall ſuggeſtion</hi> prates that the Church cannot ſtand except tyed to euery circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of pollicy and diſcipline, when indeed ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes are onely to erect democratie, and bring con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed paritie into the houſe of God, <hi>by men who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe they know God but by their workes they deny him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Flor. Scen.</note>
               <hi>Religio paſsim in ore improbitas in corde, liuor honeſti zelo perſonatur, malidicentia fucat morbum titulo liberta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17407:8"/> &amp; tam callide haec imponunt vt noſci niſi difficulter non queant, porro quia vinenum quò dulcius eò periculo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are now become <hi>Saints</hi> in ſhow, but <hi>Scithians</hi> in ſubſtance; it ſuffiſeth if we can prate of our exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall knowledge, boaſt of our verball ſpeculation, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force a ſophiſticated diſpute, diſprouing our obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to thoſe whom God hath ſet ouer vs. <hi>Tandem eo dementiae deuenimus, vt gloriemus iis, quibus erubeſcere oportebat &amp; quod vnum habemus in malis bonum perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus peccandi verecundiam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs looke with impartiall eies vpon the late pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of our owne <hi>Separatiſis,</hi> and vpon what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons their fained griefes are grounded, and we ſhall eaſily perceiue whether the Church their Mother if they diſclaime her not (as ſome already haue done) hath left her motherly care, or his Maieſty, vnto whom they owe obedience, if they haue any conſcience (which is to be doubted) hath exceeded the extent of Soueraigntie, or they their Miniſteriall function, or dutifull allegeance in impugning either the one or the other.</p>
            <p>That I may cleare this the better, and ſhew <hi>Hercules</hi> by his foot, I will leaue generals, and deſcend to my particular obſeruations picked out of a ſhort view of ſome few paſſages contained in the huge <hi>Chaos</hi> of thoſe infamous libels, which I haue already mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whether they goe current vnder the name of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doclauius, Philadelphus, Anonimus,</hi> or other titles, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſtinguiſhing audacious attempts then perſons.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:17407:9"/>
            <p>In the Epiſtle to the Altar of <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> cenſuring his Maieſties learned and Princely <hi>Baſilicon doron,</hi> theſe be the words of <hi>Didoclauius, Auaite hoſtem nobis infeſtiſsimum regem Brittanniae, &amp;c.</hi> A little after in that ſame Epiſtle, <hi>Pro principe Apoſtata non oran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum docet Apoſtolus, ordines in ordinem redigere poſſe tirannum, &amp; gladium e furioſi manibus extorquere, veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimile eſt aliquos cenſuiſſe, nam id ſentiunt viri docti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, in that Epiſtle he is not aſhamed to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime an impudent knowne vntruth in theſe words. <hi>Anno ſecundo poſt regis in Angliam aduentum</hi> 300. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtri vel libertate concionandi mulctati, v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> beneficio priuati vel excommunicationis fulmine icti, vel in carce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem coniecti, vel ſolum vertere coacti &amp;c. ſuperiorum temporum annales replicanti reperire non eſt grauiorem, ſub vllo principe fidem orthodoxam profitente perſecutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the courſe of conformitie, page 88. theſe be the words of the ſame authour; the <hi>Idolatry of</hi> Ieroboam (ſaith he) <hi>might haue as well beene defended, by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and kirke of that age, as Idolatry of this age by the State and Clergy;</hi> now ioyne all theſe together and you ſhall the better without comment, vnderſtand the one by the other, and by what ſpirit a priuate man, impudently taxing King, Clergy and Gouernment to which hee ought obedience, preferreth ſuch do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to which hee is aſhamed, otherwiſe to affixe his name, then by <hi>anagrammatizing Dauidis Calder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wodi</hi> into <hi>Edwardi Didoclauii,</hi> as if none but the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of his owne language could diſſolue ſuch a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17407:9"/> 
               <hi>Gordian</hi> knot, explaine this ſubtill <hi>Hierogliphicke,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate this labyrinthian riddle, or finde out a Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocke by the eye.</p>
            <p>To come from the Title to the Subiect, there was neuer Chriſtian pen that did blot paper with ſo bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous <hi>Aphoriſmes,</hi> ſcandalous compariſons, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honourable reproches, all which vntruthes from the mouth of a ſhameleſſe lybeller are honorable badges to vertues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Miriam</hi> was branded with leproſie,<note place="margin">Num. 12.10.</note> becauſe in bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe ſhe once reproued <hi>Moſes</hi> for his <hi>Aethiopian</hi> wife.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.5. Gen. 9.22.</note> 
               <hi>Schemei</hi> rayled but once againſt the Lords an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted, and yet had his reward. <hi>Cham</hi> but once mocked his fathers drunken nakedneſſe, and yet had his fathers curſe; but this curſed <hi>Schemei,</hi> and vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall <hi>Cham</hi> neuer ceaſeth to curſe both <hi>Prince, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> and <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and vpbrayd the comely clothed ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie of his parents, and yet looketh to be honoured as an <hi>Oracle</hi> or <hi>canonized Saint.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How dareth this <hi>Cirian</hi> Wolfe barke againſt that <hi>Moone,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stob. apud Plin.</note> whoſe light borrowed from the great <hi>eye of Heauen,</hi> diſſipates the <hi>Cimerian</hi> darkeneſſe of that night, in whoſe obſcuritie hee thirſteth to prey vpon the innocencie of vnwarie ſheepe, or think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this baſtardly brat that his Maieſtie hath not thouſands, the leaſt ſcratch of whoſe pens is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to brand his face with blacke infamie, if they wold interrupt more profitable ſtudies by honoring a factious libeller, with anſwer to beggerly collections, borrowed as well from the dregs of <hi>ſciſmaticall</hi> opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17407:10"/> as from the corrupt pudles of ſome <hi>double tongd Lawyers,</hi> and informatory papers of the <hi>ſeditious</hi> bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of his owne profeſſion,<note place="margin">Chilon opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam pronun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiauit Remp. quae maximè leges minime autem Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris audiat. Sto. Ser. 41. Non eſt opus quoties libet ogganire ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem conuitia reſellere vind. Phil. pag 951.</note> euery materiall point whereof is ſo fully already anſwered, and conuinced by men learned, truly religious and Church Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, confirmed by Parliament, the <hi>repreſentatiue body</hi> of the State, that if truth might haue truſt, or reaſon place, the chiefe maintainers of that orderleſſe frame might be ſatisfied, or giue ſentence againſt themſelues to be thruſt out of the <hi>Church</hi> for ſuch <hi>irregular,</hi> rude and intemperate <hi>paſsions,</hi> as in bitternes of gall makes a <hi>ſciſſure</hi> in the vnitie of the Church, and expoſeth the ſacred name of Soueraigntie to contempt, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther annihilates it.</p>
            <p>But leſt it be thought, that rather <hi>paſsion</hi> then <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> thus tranſports me, I will firſt examine the ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted degrees of perſecution, whereupon this <hi>trumpet</hi> of <hi>ſedition</hi> buildeth his <hi>reaſonleſſe railing,</hi> and then the dignitie of the gouernment whereof he ſo much boaſted.</p>
            <p>To come to the firſt, he aggrauates the perſecution by the number perſecuted, <hi>viz,</hi> 300. then diſcending to the perſons of ſome prime men ſo perſecuted, hee nameth Maſter <hi>Robert Bruce,</hi> Maſter <hi>Andrew</hi> and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Iames Meluils,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. Altar. Damaſc.</note> with ſome other few.</p>
            <p>The firſt, he ſaith, hath beene <hi>terra iactatus &amp; vndis,</hi> or ſubiected to the extremitie of <hi>perſecution,</hi> for the ſpace of twenty three yeeres: then after an <hi>emphaticall Epilogue</hi> of his diſcent and praiſes, hee exclaimeth, <hi>anima mea cum anima tua Bruci.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:17407:10"/>
            <p>For the praiſes due to that reuerend well diſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Gentleman, I thinke he hath ſaid too little, and that he hath deſerued the pen of a more famous Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour to <hi>blazon</hi> his commendation; but that Maſter <hi>Robert Bruce</hi> will echo a rayler, with <hi>anima mea cum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nima tua Dioclauii,</hi> is more then I will beleeue.</p>
            <p>That the leaſt touch of any ſuch ſeueritie hath bin vſed againſt Maſter <hi>Robert Bruce,</hi> it is more then him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe will confirme: the limitation of his reſidence within ſuch places where his Miniſterie might bee moſt profitable, and he leaſt troubled with ſeditious motions of violent ſpirits (whoſe inconſiderate at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts much greeueth him) was done vpon mature deliberation, and warranted with diuine and humane Lawes.</p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Andrew Meluil</hi> a learned man, whoſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, as on the one part, I will not mention without modeſt reſpect: ſo on the other part, leſt I ſhould wrong the truth, or ſmother his <hi>Maieſties gracious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect</hi> to him; I can ſay no leſſe then his intollerable <hi>fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry humour</hi> ſeconded with a miſregard of his <hi>ſuperiours</hi> and <hi>place,</hi> did precipitate him into the abridgement of his libertie. In all which time his <hi>Maieſties</hi> care was ſuch of him (as I haue heard Maſter <hi>Meluill</hi> confeſſe) that neuer ſubiect of his condition had greater fauour at libertie then he in reſtraint; neither was the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Bulloignes</hi> requeſt for his libertie, without his <hi>Maieſties</hi> knowne willingneſſe, who condeſcended at firſt, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prompted the <hi>Dukes motion.</hi> Maſter <hi>Iames Meluil</hi> a man of more mild diſpoſition and quiet temper, yet
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17407:11"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:17407:11"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:17407:12"/> ſo farre ingaged in the factious courſe of his <hi>brethren</hi> that hee could not reclaime himſelfe when (as is well knowne) hee moſt earneſtly deſired: hee li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at <hi>Berwicke</hi> with greater content, and had better meanes allowed him then euer hee had in <hi>Scotland,</hi> neither in all that time was his <hi>Maieſties</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuolence wanting.</p>
            <p>Some others of the Miniſtery that were ſentenced to exile, in mitigation of a capitall iudgement giuen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, vpon acknowledgement of their offence, were recalled and reſtored to their owne or better places.</p>
            <p>If there hath beene, or yet be, any in <hi>Scotland</hi> ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenced or confined, it was, and is, vpon their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuous miſdemeanours, and vpon mature legall proceedings againſt them; whereof the whole number (ſo farre as I can learne) doth not amount to halfe a hundreth, farre leſſe multiply to three hundred inlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the lybeller.</p>
            <p>If he calleth thoſe perſecuted Saints, whoſe bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> hath enlarged out of his Crowne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenues, he erreth not ſo much, if he had ſayd ſixe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, as he doth now in miſtaking three hundred for fiftie or fewer: but it is the nature of baſe ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, to receiue more eaſily bad impreſſions then good, to abſtract fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the realitie of benefits receiued, and aggrauate the leaſt miſconception of inuiuries offered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nihil amas cum ingratum amas, neque ſtipula leui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> pondus, quam fides eius.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:17407:12"/>
            <p>It is ſaid by that <hi>famous</hi> but dead <hi>ſtatua</hi> of <hi>Memnon</hi> did alwayes reſound cheerfull <hi>echoes,</hi> when the <hi>Suns</hi> golden <hi>Beames</hi> did ſhine vpon it; but now many li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>ſtatues</hi> in place of cheerfull <hi>acclamations</hi> of ioy and content, for ſo great benefits as they dayly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, ſend backe nothing but bitter <hi>exclamations,</hi> and whatſoeuer may <hi>eternize ingratitude</hi> whoſe bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pen writeth royall fauours in duſt, and <hi>imaginarie diſguſts</hi> in <hi>marble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Loe this is the <hi>perſecution,</hi> this the <hi>tyrranny,</hi> and theſe be the perſecuted,<note place="margin">Epiſt. Vind. Philadel.</note> 
               <hi>quibus nihil relictum niſi miſeram vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vt miſeria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſentiant.</hi> Whether this be a true hiſtory or an apochriphall fable, I appeale to impartiall cenſure, whether in the moſt ſtrict enquiry into thoſe iuſt ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maduerſions, or rather preuentions of further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt againſt the refractarie <hi>Miniſters,</hi> any thing can be found but diuine wiſedome, long <hi>patience</hi> and <hi>iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> rather ouerſeaſoned with <hi>mercy,</hi> then affected to the leaſt inclination of <hi>ſeueritie,</hi> or whether it be <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian zeale</hi> accompanied with pride, malice and contempt, or true zeale attended with <hi>Faith, Charitie,</hi> and <hi>Humilitie,</hi> that tickleth the fancy of the <hi>penman</hi> of the greateſt perſecution that can bee found in any hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory? This is the <hi>Philadelphian Euſebius</hi> and learned <hi>Rabbin</hi> that out of the <hi>Sanhedrime</hi> of his fiery braine muſt rule both Church and State by ſuch <hi>Catilina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Gloſſes,</hi> as introduce mutinous <hi>anarchie</hi> and are onely vailes to couer the face of treaſon,<note place="margin">Epiſt. Vind. Philadel.</note> that it bee not ſeene in its vgly ſhape. This is the <hi>champion Dido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clauius,</hi> whoſe <hi>Herculean</hi> labours muſt re-erect <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plinam optime ſtabilitatem &amp; feliciter adminiſtratam,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:17407:13"/> or more truely, the frame of <hi>implacable paritie,</hi> agreeing in nothing but in <hi>diſcord,</hi> and onely conſtant in <hi>incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie,</hi> as ſhall appeare by the diſcipline ſo highly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced and pictured by another brother of the purer profeſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Phil. de Reg. Eccleſ. Stob: pag. 1.</note>Although, ſayth <hi>Philadelphus,</hi> our Church acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge foure ſorts of <hi>Miniſters, Paſtors, Doctors, Elders,</hi> and <hi>Deaecons,</hi> yet the office of <hi>Doctor</hi> hath not beene in vſe otherwiſe then in the <hi>Schooles,</hi> but the reformation was effected by other three members, with the helpe of the <hi>Nobilitie</hi> and <hi>Communaltie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, then we haue a <hi>Doctor</hi> one of the foure pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of the foundation of this <hi>gouernment;</hi> yet that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Philadelphus</hi> or his brethren haue made, not onely no vſe of that name, but rather perſecuted it with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie of <hi>enuy,</hi> their bitter inuectiues againſt the late inſtitution of Doctors in <hi>Scotland</hi> will fully demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate; becauſe the title of a <hi>Doctor</hi> ſeemed to looke a little higher then <hi>paritie</hi> could well indure, they did reiect it which by time might haue ouer-topped them, and vſed the helpe of ſome of the Nobilitie and violent common people, in the reformation; the firſt were powerfull, being inueſted in the <hi>Church reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues,</hi> the other forward and fit inſtruments to advance <hi>anarchie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is a fourefold <hi>frame</hi> lam'd already of a <hi>foot</hi> by their owne records, if a <hi>politicke</hi> or <hi>naturall body</hi> may not ſubſiſt intire without a prime member.</p>
            <p>Now let vs diſtinctly examine the progreſſe of this externall gouernment, wherein firſt behold (which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17407:13"/> 
               <hi>Philadelphus</hi> ſmothereth in ſilence) the good <hi>Corne</hi> purged with the <hi>Chaffe,</hi> the <hi>Wheate</hi> with the <hi>Cockle,</hi> or the good things remoued with the bad, and the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>monuments</hi> and <hi>policie</hi> of the <hi>kingdome</hi> ouerthrown or demoliſhed by head-ſtrong <hi>violence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, that they might not ſeeme to ouerturne all <hi>order</hi> at once,<note place="margin">Philadel. p. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Biſhops</hi> that renounced <hi>Popiſme</hi> were continued, conditionally, that they ſhould maintaine <hi>Paſtors</hi> in their <hi>Dioceſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Epiſcopis qui eierato Papiſmo ad cauſam religionis ſe adiungebant conceſſum vt reditibus fruerentur, ea lege vt paſtores in ſuis dioceſibus alerent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, were <hi>ſuperintendents</hi> eſtabliſhed in the place of Biſhops as well to admit and exauctorate <hi>Miniſters</hi> as to adminiſtrate diuine ſeruice,<note place="margin">Philadel. ibid. pag. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Statuit Eccleſia ex ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectiſsimis Paſtoribus duodecem eligi, quibus daretur in deſignatis ſibi prouinciis poteſtas ſacra adminiſtrandi au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorandi &amp; exauctorandi paſtores, hos ſuperintendentes apellabant &amp; inſumptum maiori ſtipendio inſtruebant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not long after (whether the <hi>emenencie</hi> of <hi>ſuperin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendents</hi> did become ſuſpicious to <hi>generall aſſemblies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. p. 4.</note> or whether they did not keepe their accounts ſtreight, they were firſt tied to a yeerely account to the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren aſſembled; after that, certaine <hi>Commiſsioners</hi> of the <hi>Miniſtrie</hi> were adioyned to them (as it ſeemeth) to keepe them within the limits of their iniunctions, howſoeuer <hi>ſuperintendents</hi> and the former <hi>Biſhops</hi> were onely <hi>fires</hi> to <hi>premature</hi> the enſuing <hi>anarchy,</hi> thundred out by <hi>Iohn Knox,</hi> by whom the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church was wholly directed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In hoc negotio nemo neſcit maiorem Knoxii quam om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium ſuperintendentium luudem fuiſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vind. Phil. pag. 27.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:17407:14"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Phila. p. 5.</note>In the aſſembly holden at <hi>Leeth, anno</hi> 1571. <hi>Ianuary</hi> 12. <hi>Biſhops</hi> were againe eſtabliſhed, but not without oppoſition following; the next yeere in the <hi>Sinod</hi> holden at <hi>Pearthe,</hi> wherein the diſciples of <hi>Knox</hi> made earneſt proteſtation againſt the <hi>gouernment</hi> of <hi>Biſhops.</hi> Anno 1573. the <hi>generall aſſemblies</hi> did inioyne <hi>Biſhops</hi> to haue no further <hi>authoritie</hi> then <hi>ſuperintendents</hi> had before.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note>In the aſſembly holden at <hi>Edenborrough,</hi> ann. 1575. it was diſputed, whether the office of a <hi>Biſhop</hi> was a place of <hi>charge</hi> or of <hi>dignitie,</hi> a <hi>Theſis</hi> not vnlike that of the <hi>Popiſh Clergy</hi> making queſtion to whom the <hi>Lords Prayer</hi> ſhould be directed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 6.</note>In the aſſembly following at <hi>Edenborrough,</hi> anno 1576. the office of Biſhops is declared titular, and they tyed to the gouernment of one <hi>Flocke,</hi> without <hi>ſupremacy</hi> at all, ouer other <hi>Paſtours,</hi> ſo that now they are a Stage lower then <hi>ſuperintendents,</hi> with whom they were equals by the <hi>Canons</hi> of the former aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly.<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> Anno. 1577. the ſecond booke of <hi>Church gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> was confirmed and publiſhed, the <hi>Hierarchy</hi> of <hi>Biſhops</hi> condemned, and new lawes of <hi>diſcipline</hi> eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed.<note place="margin">Ibid.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In the aſſembly holden at <hi>Dundie,</hi> anno 1580. <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> were deueſted of all <hi>authority,</hi> their office decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be a humane inuention receiued to the preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of the Church, to bee razed out of the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, and they inioyned to yeeld to this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, vnder the paine of excommunication. But leſt ſuch dayly <hi>nouations</hi> might argue <hi>Proteus</hi>-like changes in this gouernment,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Philadelphus</hi> ſubioyneth a reaſon, <hi>multae erant de negligentia &amp; ignorantia Epiſcoporum
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17407:14"/> quaerelae.</hi> Such lips, ſuch latice, or a mad concluſion of a fond propoſition, as if I ſhould ſay, becauſe <hi>Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delphus, Didoclauius</hi> and the like <hi>fire-brands</hi> are the ſtaines of the Miniſtry, and diſturbers of the Church; therefore the <hi>office</hi> of all Paſtors is vtterly to be defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and forbidden: the caſes are matches, if the one may ſtand in <hi>Law,</hi> the other may; and if we condemne the one, wee muſt condemne the other; for, if we reaſon from the abuſe of good things to the remouing of them, we ſhall fall into an <hi>anarchy</hi> and ouerthrow all <hi>reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the aſſembly holden at <hi>Glaſcow,</hi> 1581. Aprill 24.<note place="margin">Ibid. pag. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Presbiteriall gouernment,</hi> and what elſe might aduance <hi>democratie,</hi> was eſtabliſhed, and continued without great encreaſe, till the aſſembly holden 1590. that <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie</hi> began to waxe like a <hi>gourd;</hi> then were <hi>Commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners</hi> or <hi>Prouinciall ouer-ſeers</hi> diſcharged, and their power conferred vpon <hi>Presbiteriall</hi> aſſemblies, as the vndoubted right of thoſe <hi>pupils</hi> that were but nine yeeres of age.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Comiſsionariorum ſiue viſitatorum prouinciarum po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtas abrogata eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. p. 6.</note> 
               <hi>eorumque munus Presbiteriis tanquam ius ſuum conceſſum eſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. p. 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>From the beginning of <hi>Presbiteriall</hi> gouernment vnto anno 1600. or thereabouts, by the records of generall, prouincial, presbiteriall aſſemblies, and <hi>Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiall ſeſsions,</hi> nothing is to be found but the <hi>Auſtrian plus vltra</hi> dayly encroacht vpon, and euery day new deuiſes. In the time of this raging confuſion <hi>Maieſty</hi> was ouer-ſwayed with clamourous railing, faction in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited, maintained and defended by <hi>adherence</hi> of moſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17407:15"/> part of the <hi>Miniſtrie</hi> to the ſtrongeſt partie of thoſe <hi>combuſtions,</hi> that were too common in thoſe dayes, but <hi>now</hi> are happily remoued by the wiſdome of that <hi>King,</hi> whom refractarie <hi>furies</hi> hath from his very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancie ſo <hi>barbarouſly, inſolently,</hi> and <hi>vnthankefully</hi> oppoſed, that by <hi>diuine</hi> and <hi>nationall Lawes</hi> iuſtly might hee haue curbed ſuch <hi>madneſſe</hi> with a more ſtrict <hi>cenſure,</hi> then by his milde and <hi>royall</hi> regrate in his learned <hi>Princely Baſilicon Doron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. Altar Damaſc.</note> that he had found more trueth and loyaltie, amongſt the dregs of his Subiects, then with thoſe, who againſt all modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the conſcience of their profeſſion, had left no practiſe vnaſſayed againſt Soueraigntie, that either faction or vulgar applauſe could <hi>conciliate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might add here many rare <hi>paradoxes,</hi> inſolent <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanours,</hi> and bold <hi>attempts,</hi> not beſeeming Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſobrietie, much leſſe the approbation of a well ſettled gouernment: but if it appeare, that eithet the frame or adminiſtration pictured by <hi>Philadelphus,</hi> bee orderly or any way ſorting with an happy gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I deſire to know what is <hi>anarchie,</hi> diſloyaltie and ſedition? but I leaue the preſſure of ſuch feſtered ſores, and continue my <hi>enquirie</hi> in the late actions of that <hi>impure Spawne</hi> of thoſe <hi>Separatiſts</hi> whoſe <hi>Grachus</hi> doctrine, <hi>Catechiſme</hi> of <hi>ſedition</hi> &amp; ſchoole of <hi>faction</hi> is neither <hi>compatible</hi> with the Lawes of God or Empire, or any thing elſe then the ouer flowing of the ſurfet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſtomach of <hi>Muncer</hi> the Anabaptiſt, who drunke in ſelfe-conceit, did boſt to conquer the world with the ſword of the <hi>Spirit: Et cogere vniuerſum orbem gladio Gedeonis ad nonum Chriſti regnum inſtituendum:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gual. Tug:</note>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:17407:15"/> But leſt any man ſhould doubt of the perfection of the gouernment ſo highly aduanced,<note place="margin">Philadelp. p. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Philadelphus</hi> crownes it with <hi>tum quidem bene currebamus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is well ſaid Sir, yet giue me leaue to tell you, that oft times the more haſte the worſe ſpeede, and that <hi>feſtina lente</hi> in gouernment is more ſure, and commeth oft times more ſafely home, then that hot ſpurre, that either ſpoyles his horſe, or runneth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe out of winde or ioynt; or as your <hi>anarchie</hi> that was rotten before it was ripe. Yet let vs heare an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable gloſſe vpon an Apocriphall text, or the reaſon which <hi>Philadelphus</hi> giueth, that this happines was interrupted by the bringing in of Biſhops.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diabolus</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>hanc faelicitatem inuidens terti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Epiſcoporum genus noua arte ſuppoſuit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Philad. ibid.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For anſwer to ſuch prophane cenſures, I can ſay no leſſe, then that as his former running courſe did ſhew more will then wiſdome, and hath ſhortned the life of conſiſtorian diſcipline and prematured violence: ſo is his ragged reaſon againſt all reaſon or probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, that the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>darkeneſſe</hi> and confuſion ſhould enuy <hi>anarchy,</hi> and haue any hand in the <hi>frame</hi> of good <hi>gouernment,</hi> which is a chiefe <hi>type</hi> of Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and the <hi>ſnafle</hi> that curbeth the <hi>pride, ſelfe-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit</hi> and <hi>preſumption</hi> of vnſtayed <hi>ſpirits,</hi> who oft times in repining againſt <hi>Magiſtracy,</hi> are authours in their owne <hi>deſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus haue you heard, how <hi>Didoclauius</hi> and <hi>Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delphus</hi> doe tilt at <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Clergy;</hi> now you ſhall heare another <hi>bird</hi> of that ſame <hi>feather</hi> runne the <hi>wild-Gooſe</hi> chaſe at <hi>Councell</hi> and <hi>Court,</hi> taking aime through a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17407:16"/> falſe looking glaſſe, lately framed by a Scotiſh Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiſt, and ſteeled or put in a rauing ſtile at <hi>Leiden</hi> by an Engliſh <hi>Browniſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Specul. bell. Sacr. pag. 97.</note>A forme-changing <hi>Proteus</hi> (ſaith this new Doctor) a trecherous <hi>Seianus,</hi> a time ſeruing <hi>Abiathar,</hi> a <hi>Stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Achitophel,</hi> a <hi>calumniating Doeg,</hi> are the only <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours:</hi> but <hi>Conſtantine</hi> tryed his <hi>Courtiers</hi> fidelitie to him, by their piety towards God; but now a man truly religious, is thought vnfitteſt for ſtate affairs,<note n="a" place="margin">The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors reaſon.</note> becauſe they cannot ſay he is an honeſt man; but with this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionall, if he were not a ranke <hi>Puritan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt part of this bold vntrue calumny, deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth rather the examination of a whip then of a pen, or of a pillory then of a reply; yet I wiſh that the fond foole, the Authour, ſhould know that his <hi>Maieſty</hi> hath moe, truly <hi>religious, wiſe, learned, loyall Councellours</hi> and <hi>Courteours,</hi> then there be honeſt men <hi>Puritans</hi> of his opinion in the whole world, in which large <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference</hi> I doe verily thinke there is not one.</p>
            <p>On the contrary, I may truly affirme, that there be few <hi>Courts</hi> or <hi>Stateſmen</hi> in <hi>Europe,</hi> or elſewhere can <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralell,</hi> none exceed either the <hi>fidelity</hi> or <hi>integrity</hi> of thoſe in great <hi>Britaine:</hi> if all be not a like affected, or any, otherwiſe enclined, then human eyes can ſee, or the <hi>wiſdome</hi> of a <hi>wiſe King</hi> preuent, God muſt be their iudge, and their conſcience their witneſſe. A <hi>runnagate</hi> that hath put his hand from <hi>Gods plough,</hi>
               <note place="margin">This Lybeller was once a Miniſter, but did lately co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke at Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</note> and turned <hi>Quackeſaluer,</hi> is not to cenſure thoſe whom he ought not to name but with honourable humble reſpect. The <hi>brethren</hi> of his owne <hi>profeſſion,</hi> whom he calleth truly religious, and whom in all his <hi>applications</hi> hee
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17407:16"/> thinketh the only able men to rule both <hi>Church, Court</hi> and <hi>Campe,</hi> are thought vnfit (as he ſaith) for State af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires; To that part I anſwer, that euery good ſubiect hath great cauſe to thanke God that our <hi>King</hi> is more wiſe, then to admit any into his <hi>Councell</hi> or affaires of <hi>State,</hi> whom all men (beſides themſelues) know to be fairded with falſe colours of <hi>religion,</hi> and more fit to be <hi>fagots</hi> for <hi>combuſtion</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> then to be hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers in ſupporting the heauy frame of Empire; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe diſeaſes of this kinde are hereditary to moſt of this family, infuſing from one to another, a taint or ſtaggers in their vitall ſpirits, as if they were bitten with a mad Dog, which frenzie maketh them vnſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable, either in Church or Commonwealth, but ſpecially to bee vncapable to bee vpon Councell of Kings, who are the onely barres that impeach their proceedings, for this cauſe they cunningly labour to induce the people to condole their yoke of obedience caſt off ſuch fetters, and purchaſe their libertie.</p>
            <p>The reaſon which the Doctor giueth, is like his phyſicall receipts which trouble his patients more then the diſeaſe: for certainly, if we may call theſe <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans,</hi> whom this <hi>lybeller</hi> eſteemeth to be ſo; <hi>King, Councell,</hi> and <hi>Court,</hi> haue iuſt cauſe to take exception at the very name which is but a ſtaine of <hi>Puritaniſme;</hi> for my part, if it bee lawfull to iudge men by their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: I may ſafely ſay, that he can neuer be an honeſt man to God and to his countrey, that conceiueth ſuch damnable thoughts, farre leſſe he that publiſheth ſuch helliſh poſitions, and that beſides all other poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable traſh euery where intermixt in this <hi>Doctors bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17407:17"/> pilles,</hi> this one <hi>Colaquintida</hi> ſo corrupts all his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther drugs, that it proclaimeth him to to be an impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent rayler, a <hi>Pſeudo-puritan,</hi> or rotten hearted <hi>hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite,</hi> and not a <hi>Puritan,</hi> of which number I wiſh my ſelfe, and all others to be, if human infirmitie might aime at ſuch perfection, ſo long as it is clothed with mortalitie.</p>
            <p>But thus it falleth out, that as well the beſt men as their beſt actions ſet and performed, on the <hi>conſpicuous Theater</hi> of the world, are alwayes attended and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with blacke detraction and calumnie, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Brats of malecontents, ignorance or enuy, who loath the <hi>Nectar</hi>-like drops that fall from heauen vpon ſweet flowers, and delight onely to ſucke the poyſonable iuyce of gall and wormwood.</p>
            <p>Hence it is that factious ſpirits, violently <hi>agitated</hi> with outragious paſſion of <hi>ſingularitie,</hi> enuy, anger, deſire of rule, and popular applauſe, are onely quiet in commotions,<note place="margin">Stob. apud. Plut.</note> peaceable in tumults, happy in cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, diſaffecting no leſſe <hi>amicable concord,</hi> then <hi>regal</hi> power and authoritie, thereby offring vnto Gods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties and their iuſt commands, the peſts and poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of their infected and ill affected minds, imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thoſe barbarous nations, who in their ſacrifices did offer the gall and vileſt parts of their beaſts. What can we call the malitious cenſuring of <hi>ſacred perſons,</hi> or deſignes, but a kind of <hi>ſacriledge</hi> and <hi>blaſphemy,</hi> both againſt God and Kings, of whom all diſcourſe ought to be full of Religion, reuerence and reſpect?</p>
            <p>O mercifull God! what wit is able to ſound the depth of thoſe dangerous euils, whereinto the malitious
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17407:17"/> nature of <hi>ſciſmaticall ſedition</hi> vailed with religion, is able to ſinke it ſelfe, rather then to acknowledge error in thoſe things which it hath taken vpon it to defend,<note place="margin">Courſe of conformitie. pag. 88.</note> againſt the ſtreame of publike reſolution, ranked in the eyes of <hi>ſingularitie,</hi> with the moſt <hi>tyrannous</hi> gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that euer did ſee the Sun?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Miſerum eſt peccare, miſerius delectari, miſerrimum excuſare, &amp; tum demum conſumata amentia eſt cum ad ſtudium malum opinio quedam pietatis acceſserit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The motto of <hi>Iacke Straw, Wyat</hi> &amp; <hi>Kett</hi> was <hi>viuat E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> &amp; now the pretext of conſcience is a cullour of diſobedience to euery caſheerd <hi>Leuite</hi> or ignorant <hi>conſiſtorian,</hi> whoſe ſtudies are by wreſting Scripture to deſtroy vnitie, beget a ſciſme in the hearts or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, and make it their common place in writings, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, or in the Pulpit to leape from the liues of their flockes, to enueigh againſt gouernment, and preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly incroach without all reuerence vpon the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of Princes, as they were able to demoliſh the walles of the Church, ſhake the foundations of the State, and liue Libertines without controlement.</p>
            <p>When authoritie commaundeth any thing that is to be preſumed not againſt, but for aduancement of Religion; I would gladly know who is to be <hi>confer,</hi> whether the things commanded be lawfull or not, or whether ſome <hi>ſingular</hi> contentious or malecontented ſpirits, tranſported with wrong ends, may oppoſe the Church in his <hi>Maieſties</hi> lawes, giuing life vnto them? If <hi>Authoritie</hi> at any time ſwerue from the ſtrict ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruance of religion, in its owne integritie, in matters of diſcipline, that remiſſenes ought to incite Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17407:18"/> to deuotion and pietie, to explaine the ſenſe of Scripture with all humilitie, to acquaint as well <hi>Princes</hi> as people, with the will of God by preaching, to turne the wrath of God from them by prayer; that ſo obtaining a bleſſing vpon their labours, they may by practiſe confirme ſuch in the faith by their workes, as they haue wonne by their words to embrace and beleeue it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ex pede Herculem,</hi> the tree is knowne by the fruite, and not by the floriſhing ſhadowes of ſubſtance. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation and railing, howſoeuer perſonated in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious habit, is not ſo much to the preſeruation of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion as the <hi>Romans</hi> did <hi>ſuperſtitiouſly</hi> imagine the <hi>keckling</hi> of <hi>Geeſe</hi> was to the ſafety of the <hi>Capitolium.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambroſ. ſerm. de obed,</note> Contentious bitterneſſe is as oppoſite to the peace of the Church, as oyle to the quenching of fire. God is not in the bitter diuiſion or <hi>alienation</hi> of affections, nor in the raging fire of <hi>ſeditions,</hi> nor in <hi>turbulent tempeſts</hi> and <hi>whirlewinds</hi> of <hi>contradictions</hi> and <hi>diſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> But <hi>his bleſſed Spirit is in the ſweet gentle breach and ſtill calme winde of peace and concord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any man ſay, they are warranted by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, contentiouſly to impugne authoritie, <hi>anull</hi> the lawes of a free <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and make a <hi>Metamorhpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> of religion, at their pleaſure when euery miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception tickleth their fancy: I anſwer that they balke the high way wherein they ought to walke, neglect the maine end at which they ſhould driue, and aime <hi>obliquely</hi> at priuate gaine, vaine glory, ſatisfaction of ſome baſe humour or paſſion. If our conſcience tels vs this or that, and cannot proue what it tells, but by
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17407:18"/> ſhifts, coniectures &amp; ſhadows; then it is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience at leaſt no true, but a lying conſcience, that ſo miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leads vs; no, it is rather our fancy, our peeuiſh pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudicate and forward conceit, which we are bound to reſiſt and ſubiect our owne peruerſe crooked will to the will of God;<note place="margin">Melanch. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pirom. Philoſ.</note> who hath <hi>ſubiected</hi> vs to lawfull <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates,</hi> whoſe hearts are ſo deepe and vnſearchable, by reaſon of the <hi>multiplicitie</hi> of affaires, and variable waies they are forced to walke for the weale of their people, that oft times when they ſeem to erre to theſe; who ought to bee holden in ſuſpence, or that vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not the language of State, their actions tels their wiſdome to the world, as well in protecting their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects within, as curbing their enemies abroad. In con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration whereof, the booke of publike determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on once opened, euery <hi>liege</hi> man is to <hi>acquieſſe</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; becauſe Kings are Gods deputies to execute <hi>iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> and iudgement, and to leuell ſingular oppoſitions by lawes eſtabliſhed; if they doe it not, the fault is theirs, to whom the preuention of contempt, or ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maduerſion into ſuch lawes doth belong.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Micha</hi> will ſet vp an <hi>Idoll</hi> and aſſume a cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber worſhip to ſatisfie his erring conſcience,<note place="margin">Iudg. 17.5.6.</note> the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is ſubioyned, becauſe there was no King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but euery man did what ſeemed good in his owne eies. <hi>Conſcientia non eſt contra ſcientia ſed cum ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> our conſcience muſt bee ioyned with knowledge, otherwiſe we <hi>Idolatrze</hi> vnto our owne hearts, whilſt we obay an ignorant or etring conſcience; howſoeuer it may ſeeme right in the eyes of <hi>ſciſmaticks,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prouer. 14.12</note> yet ſuch a conſcience is but a melancholy imagination or <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuolent</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:17407:19"/> inuention, the end whereof are the wayes of death.</p>
            <p>As the Lawes of God muſt guide our conſciences in matters of Faith: ſo the poſitiue Lawes of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome muſt be the high way wherin euery good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect muſt walke, in actiue obedience, in matters not repugnant to that faith.</p>
            <p>Againe, <hi>Kings</hi> are diſpenſators and dilpoſers of the law, but they are not holden to ſatisfie euery priuate contentious or curious head, which pretend conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for diſobedience, or anſwer euery delinquent with arguments; if they did ſo, their worke were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite. It is ſtrange then in the eyes of ſound iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that ſome rebellious factious ſpirits ſhould thus roare, range, &amp; rage as if we had neither <hi>Prince Prieſt</hi> nor <hi>Iudge.</hi> The Apoſtles and Fathers obayed <hi>Nero</hi> a <hi>Monſter</hi> and <hi>Tyrant; Diocleſian</hi> a cruell <hi>perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> and <hi>Iulian</hi> an accurſed <hi>Apoſtate.</hi> When there was not a Chriſtian King vpon earth, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>Titus</hi> to <hi>put the people in remembrance of their obedience to Princes and Rulers. Neque aliud remedium proponitur priuatis hominibus tirannis ſubiectis, preter preces &amp; lachrymas &amp; vitae mendationem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There can bee no iuſt cauſe enabling ſubiects to arme againſt authoritie; becauſe a publike action muſt be warranted with a iuſt cauſe, a good intention, and lawfull authoritie; the laſt whereof can neuer fall into priuate hands, which are not to <hi>vendicate</hi> that <hi>cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance</hi> which belongeth to the tribunall of heauen.</p>
            <p>That tranſcendent <hi>Maieſtie</hi> by whom <hi>Kings</hi> raigne hath reſerued their <hi>audit</hi> to himſelfe, that they may be
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17407:19"/> more carefull to keepe their accompts ſtreight and rule with iuſtice. The <hi>Iura Regalia</hi> of <hi>Kings</hi> are holden of heauen and cannot eſcheat to any earthly power, farre leſſe to a ſubiect. The Law hath two properties, the one to ſhew men what they ſhould doe, the other to puniſh the tranſgreſſors; the king hath intereſt in the firſt, but is not further ſubiect to the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d then to his <hi>Soueraign</hi> in <hi>heauen,</hi> whoſe deputie he is in this inferior <hi>Orbe</hi> of the earth. All <hi>popular</hi> commotions, vnreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble railing, vomiting of vnchriſtian ſcandall, <hi>factious conſpiracies,</hi> and treaſonable <hi>practices,</hi> are the badges of diſloyall and treacherous ſubiects, who ought to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the patience of true <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and the obedience of true Chriſtians. <hi>Arma mea preces meae, nec poſſum nec de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beo aliter reſiſtere,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.3.</note> The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tels vs, <hi>That we are to doe nothing in the Church through con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention or vaine glory, but that in meekneſſe of minde e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man thinke another better then himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Supporting one another through loue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.23.</note> 
               <hi>endeauouring to keepe the vnitie of faith in the bonds of peace, doing all things without reaſoning and murmuring.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the end of the Commandements is Loue out of a pure heart and of a good conſcience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.14. Tim. 1.56.</note> 
               <hi>and of faith vnfaign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, from which things ſome haue erred and turned vnto vaine ianglings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, in contempt of theſe Oracles of direction, the diſcourſe of religion doth ſo buſie the world,<note place="margin">Epiſt. hiſtor. the word.</note> that it hath well neere driuen the practice of it out of the world, where charitie and trueth haue onely their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in termes, as the <hi>Philoſophers materia prima.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Religious diſcourſe is now ſo canuaſed in the mouth of moſt men, yea at the tipling table of euery Scoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17407:20"/> Drab, vayled with the name of a <hi>Siſter,</hi> that any man might reſolue that tooke notice of their zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous diſcourſe, <hi>patheticall</hi> griefes and not of their liues that there were nothing in their deſires, but the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of heauen, and that they vſed the world as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing place towards their <hi>celeſtiall</hi> habitation; when on the contrary their actions tell the world that they are but <hi>Comedians</hi> in religion, whilſt they act <hi>diuine voice,</hi> but in their liues renounce both their perſons, and the parts they play. Curioſitie, Singularitie, and Faction,<note place="margin">Althuſ. Pol. c. 2.</note> are the three euill ſpirits that haue euer trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the world, and yet rage amongſt <hi>Separatiſts</hi> in our Northerne Climate, where, we may behold Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſitie by peſtilent vapours aſcending from prowd ſtomackes, make queſtion of euery principle of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued trueth: wee may ſee that Singularity apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the <hi>Theorems</hi> of Curioſitie, will Iudge and rule all,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.5.</note> and labour to ſteale mens hearts, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade their conſciences, that they ſhall be like vnto gods.</p>
            <p>Who is ſo blinde that he ſeeth not Faction, as <hi>Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gellum Dei,</hi> ſtriuing to arme Curioſitie and Singulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie with power to afflict their Contradictors? Theſe be the 3. corrupted ſprings that ſend out ſuch <hi>impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous inundations</hi> of ſtrife, that labour to ouerflow, the peace of the Church and ingroſſe Gods true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to ſuch prodigals that are not <hi>initiate</hi> in the firſt <hi>elements</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> duties.<note place="margin">Bruſ. lib. 35.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Phelautia,</hi> and <hi>Phantaſia</hi> ſo ſwelleth their hearts with pride, and loade their heads with diſtraction that they run into deſperate courſes as <hi>Furies,</hi> neither regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Maieſtie</hi> nor <hi>Lawes,</hi> preferring confuſion to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17407:20"/> 
               <hi>Anarchie</hi> to <hi>Monarchie,</hi> as if <hi>Imperium in imperio querendum eſſet,</hi> a <hi>Soueraigne</hi> ſhould be commanded by a ſubiect, or the body be aboue the head.</p>
            <p>If any aske them by what warrant they doe theſe things, preſently they apply all things ſpoken by <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> touching the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing of the Citie of God or the walles thereof, as the Holy Ghoſt had meant to foreſignifie, what euery Mercenary firebrand of their profeſſion ſhould doe or ſuffer, for whatſoeuer poſition without reaſon, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt authoritie, he taketh vpon him to defend; yea ſome impudent Stoickes amongſt them will tel you, <hi>who knoweth but they be the men?</hi> In their ordinary diſcourſe &amp; <hi>plagiarie paſquils,</hi> they aſſume the titles of Gods perſecuted <hi>Saints,</hi> the <hi>ſecret ones</hi> for whom God ſpared the world, <hi>Gods elect veſſels, his deere children</hi> and the like attributes,<note place="margin">Theſe be the titles which Didoclauius giueth to his brethren eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where in his Satyres. Gen. 27.22.</note> rather beſeeming the <hi>Prologue</hi> of <hi>Miles glorioſus,</hi> then to be the aſſumptions of ſober Chriſtians, but godly names doe not iuſtifie godleſſe men, they are but vpbraided when they are honoured with titles whereunto their liues are not ſutable. Many haue <hi>Iacobs voyce</hi> and <hi>Eſaus</hi> roughneſſe, words of pietie but actions of <hi>Babel</hi> and the pride of <hi>Lucifer</hi> in the <hi>inſatiable</hi> aſpiring to rule both <hi>Church</hi> and State, or bee gouerned by none of them;<note place="margin">Tertul. de preſcr.</note> but it were good ſuch men would conſider that Sathan finds more difficultie in ouerthrowing a humble ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner then proud Saint.</p>
            <p>If we looke vpon the peaceable conuerſation of the moſt earneſt <hi>Champions</hi> of <hi>Puritaniſme,</hi> we ſhall finde their chiefe Treaties of peace are <hi>extrema non media,</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:17407:21"/> rather to continue the flame then quench the fire, and to encreaſe malice then to preuent miſchiefe. To leaue thoſe of the <hi>Miniſtrie</hi> that are ſo tainted with <hi>ſophiſticated tincture</hi> of <hi>Pſeudo Puritaniſme,</hi> and come to the laytie, either in the country or cittie that are ſquared by that frame, the moſt part of the firſt ſort (I ſpeake not of all) are rigorous <hi>exactors</hi> vpon their poore hunger-ſtarued tenants, not ſparing to ſucke their <hi>blood,</hi> grind their <hi>faces</hi> and expoſe them to the extremitie of <hi>miſerie,</hi> before they want the leaſt part of their rent, which the ground curſed for ſuch merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe <hi>oppreſsion</hi> refuſeth to yeeld. If any man <hi>deprecate</hi> ſuch <hi>crueltie;</hi> their anſwer is ready, wee take but our owne, which God alloweth to euery man. If any ſtrange <hi>beggar</hi> cry at their gates, he muſt be ſent backe to his pariſh of to the ſtockes; but to acquit them of this inhumanitie, I wiſh that euery pariſh were able to maintaine their owne poore, and I commend ſuch <hi>pollicie</hi> as a <hi>type</hi> of good <hi>gouernment:</hi> yet, if ſometimes ſome <hi>hunger-ſtarued beggers,</hi> ſtraggle without their <hi>pariſh,</hi> I thinke it more charity to releeue their halfe famiſht life, then without Chriſtian compaſſion to ſend them away, or add <hi>cold</hi> to <hi>hunger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others, in Cities or Townes, knowne by the vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped title of the <hi>pure profeſsion,</hi> are ſorted in <hi>Lawyers Merchants, Mechanickes,</hi> or vnder Officers of <hi>commerce</hi> the end of whoſe calling is, or ſhould be, by <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mutatiue</hi> iuſtice to ſupply the <hi>neceſsitie</hi> of each other. The <hi>Lawy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> or <hi>Aduocate</hi> is truely to lay open the Law, for the determination of controuerſies and preſeruation of peace; neither wanteth the kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> 
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:17407:21"/> men both <hi>religious</hi> and learned of this ſort, but it is to be feared, that in it there be <hi>Pſeudo Puritans</hi> that hould <hi>non eſt iuſto lex poſita,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Timot. 1.9.</note> as if there were not a Law for ſuch <hi>Lawyers,</hi> but that they may demeane themſelues, as if they were aboue the <hi>Law,</hi> and take what cauſe they liſt in hand though they know it to be vniuſt. Their office (ſay they) is not to iudge, but to pleade, and therefore they ſpeake with more affection and earneſtneſſe againſt the <hi>trueth</hi> then for it; a good cauſe will ſpeake for it ſelfe, but he deſerues praiſe that maintaines a bad cauſe well: this is the way to make him famous, get Clyents, and ſo wealth.</p>
            <p>Although the Law limits takings, and cals the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe <hi>extortion;</hi> yet the pureſt <hi>brother</hi> of this kind may take what fees he will: this <hi>lex loquens,</hi> or tongue of the <hi>Law,</hi> can tell his <hi>Clients</hi> that the intention of the <hi>Law</hi> is to limit men that they ſhould take no leſſe, and it confines ſuch that can get no more. In other <hi>voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> ſuch as haue taken a <hi>valuable conſideration</hi> for their paines, are lyable to the cenſure of the <hi>Law,</hi> if they performe not their worke, yet theſe notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their Fee, may ſpeake or hold their peace as they pleaſe: for though they haue two hands to take Fees on both ſides, yet haue they but one tongue, and that is double, which may giue councell to both, but cannot ſpeake bu for one at once. <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> had as much for holding his peace, as <hi>Aeſchines</hi> had for plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. The <hi>doctrine</hi> of <hi>reſtitution</hi> is a <hi>Popiſh</hi> point, and the name of <hi>Catholike,</hi> though in the Creed they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abyde. In all other things they like well to be <hi>vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall,</hi> that is to be for euery man, or to bee for one
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17407:22"/> man, in one caſe, and againſt him in another, in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>reſemblance.</hi> How can a brother of the <hi>conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian congregation</hi> walke wrong that hath the Law, the rule of equitie in his hand, &amp; the <hi>immunitie</hi> of aſſumed <hi>euangelicall</hi> libertie? but the iſſue oft times declares that thoſe wayes are not right, and that <hi>male parta, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le dilabuntur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, let vs look vpon the <hi>Merchants</hi> &amp; Tradeſmen the brethren of ſeparation, and we ſhall ſee that they propound priuate gaine to themſelues, as the maine end of their ſeeming deuotion; that vnder this co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they thinke it tollerable to cheat or couſen what they can, either by <hi>ſophiſticated</hi> wares, falſe weights and meaſures, or by any other cloſe deuice ſealed by yea and nay; becauſe it is a prayſe worth part of their trade, a <hi>myſtery</hi> of their profeſſion, without which they cannot be thought to be good husbands, or thought fit to deale in the world, and for warrant, forſooth they will tell you,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.16.</note> with a whyning voyce, <hi>Chriſt</hi> comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth <hi>vs to be ſimple as Doues, but wiſe like Serpents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They are ſtrict obſeruers of euery dutie in the firſt Table, which touch not the corruption of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; but for workes of mercy commanded of the ſecond Table, they know not what they meane or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps thinke them <hi>ſuperſtitous</hi> though they heare God himſelfe ſay,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>I will haue mercy, and not ſacrifice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They wil not ſweare perhaps that is to open a ſin for their purpoſe; but if lyes wil <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their ill conditioned co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities, they wil let none <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor none lye beyond them. In a word, they make no conſcience to gaine by whatſomeuer courſe cloaked with a faigned
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17407:22"/> ſhow of deuotion. The reſidue of the life allotted to this ſhort taske, ſhould faile me, if I ſhould inſiſt vpon the <hi>Antipathie</hi> betwixt their profeſſion, manners, and life, or if I ſhould bring ſome of thoſe beſt-masked hypocrites vpon the Stage, I ſhould neede no other colours to paint them, nor penſill to delineate them, but their owne: but in diſtaſte of the lauiſh ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Tongues and corrupted Pens of moſt of their profeſſion, I will forbeare and hold it Religion, not to inſult ouer any mans <hi>perſonall</hi> infirmities; I loue bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>point</hi> at publike <hi>diſeaſes,</hi> then to <hi>launce</hi> priuate <hi>vlcerous</hi> ſores. I haue no further ayme at any mans perſon, then may conduce to the truth of this Subiect, and vindicate wronged Innocencie from the inuenomed Shafts of forged Calumnie and Malice. I balke ſecret Conuenticles, <hi>Loue-Feaſts,</hi> Chamber-Exerciſes, gauding <hi>Pilgrimages,</hi> and <hi>ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> Exhortatories, more vehement then if <hi>Turciſme</hi> or <hi>Iudaiſme</hi> were ſet vp, and Religion layed at the ſtake. I could point at euery <hi>Mirmidon,</hi> as well in their <hi>Presbiteriall</hi> as <hi>Conſiſtorian, Achilles;</hi> at the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of the Inſtructions ſent to <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of the <hi>Catilinarian</hi> Workes of <hi>Didoclauius Anonimus,</hi> and <hi>Philadelphus;</hi> by what Conuoyes the brethrens Contribution was ſent, and who returned huge Volumes of <hi>ſeditious Libels,</hi> printed at a dearer rate, then the abaters would willingly haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed eyther vpon <hi>Subſidie, Hoſpitall,</hi> or other more <hi>pious</hi> vſes.</p>
            <p>But I will not inſiſt vpon thoſe <hi>cauterized</hi> ſores,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17407:23"/> whoſe inſenſible eſtates I ought rather to condole and ſollcite remorſe, then by vnfolding my knowledge, <hi>animate</hi> authoritie ſo much prouoked and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Neither am I ſo vaine glorious apprehenſiue as to thinke my ſelfe able to raiſe the leaſt duſt with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feet then my owne, to worke vpon more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent iudgements, or with my weake Oratory perſwade them to any courſe beyond their naturall inclination: but if I ſhould aime at what may bee obiected, I ſhould do no more then perhaps ſome would do, if I were arraigned at the barre of their iudgement.</p>
            <p>Therefore, as it is no part of my ſecret meaning to draw any good ſubiect into contempt; ſo neither will I ſet any fairer maske vpon the face of this cauſe then naked trueth will afford. What I write is as far ſhort of that which I might write, as a ſhadow of ſubſtance, <hi>ſciſmaticall</hi> opinions from trueth, bitter railing from Chriſtian charity, or a ſtopper of the ſhot which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth. Military errors are euer dangerous, and oft-times irrecouerable, but diſcourſe curtailed or ſhrunk through want of inſtruction or meditation may bee regained by further ſearch, or lengthened vpon the tenter hookes of better opportunitie, without preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of preſent inabilities.</p>
            <p>What encreaſe <hi>ſciſmaticall</hi> talents haue yeelded, what confuſion of order, &amp; breach of the ſacred bond of loue hath ſprung from theſe contentions, euery mans experience hath found; the authors haue beene blinded with the beames of <hi>ſingularitie,</hi> malice or ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and the world with pretext of zeale, conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17407:23"/> and deuotion: by them the ſheepe haue beene taught to deſpiſe their <hi>Paſtors</hi> &amp; the hearts of their <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors alienated</hi> from the loue of their <hi>flockes.</hi> Such wrangling hath ſo <hi>eclipſed</hi> the face of <hi>humilitie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> charity</hi> and common <hi>honeſtie,</hi> that moſt men are now igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that the ſtorehouſe of the Church is full, when ſhe is rich in good works, and when Chriſt her ſpouſe is <hi>fed, clothed,</hi> and <hi>viſited</hi> in his hungry, naked, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed <hi>members.</hi> Our vnnaturall diuiſions haue killed the vety heart of deuotion, with-holden many zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous <hi>Paſtors</hi> and dutifull ſubiects from the building of the <hi>Sanctuarie</hi> and the publike ſeruice,<note place="margin">Nehe. 4.17.</note> or forced them with <hi>Nehemiah</hi> to build with one hand, and oppoſe the violence of theſe times with the other. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people are ſo toſſed betwixt error and trueth, that their hearts are layed open, and themſelues made naked to receiue euery impreſſion of corruption and vanity. By reaping thoſe bitter fruites of conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Separatiſts like <hi>blind guides ſtraine out a Gnat and ſwallow a Camell:</hi> they haue <hi>left the weightier matters of the Law, Iudgement, Mercie and Fidelitie;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 23.24.</note> 
               <hi>theſe things they ought to doe, and theſe things whilſt they contend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, leſſe they leaue vndone.</hi> But happyer ſhall they bee whom the Lord when hee commeth findeth doing thoſe things, then thoſe whom vnawares he ſhall ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, <hi>contentiouſly</hi> diſputing, either about thoſe <hi>curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> that are aboue heauen or vnder earth, <hi>Res quam nec ſcire datum, nec ſcrutari religioſum;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Flor. Scon. Embl.</note> or about the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward frame of diſcipline, and other friuolous que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions ſo much <hi>agitate</hi> after publike determination.</p>
            <p>In matters of the firſt kinde, we are rather religiouſly
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17407:24"/> to admire and reuerence thoſe myſteries and ſecrets of Gods councel, which he hath not reuealed, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fondly to looke vpon that <hi>Sun,</hi> whoſe brightnes is able to da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zle our eies, perhaps depriue vs of ſight, if we approch too neere to thoſe ſacred fires, whoſe ſcorching heate will rather conſume then cheriſh our cold capacitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vna &amp; quidem maxime laudabilis audacia hic, nihil audere, vnum acumen nihil cernere, vna ſcientia nihil ſcire</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In matters of policie and externall gouernment queſtionable of the ſecond ſort, it hath beene the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of former ages to follow the wayes of peace, to honour, reuerence and obey, next vnto the voyce of God, the ordinances of the Church wherein they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. <hi>Si Eccleſiae non audiuerit ſit tibi tanquam ethnicus &amp; publicanus.</hi> But now <hi>Didoclauius</hi> and his brethren thinke themſelues too glorious to ſtoope to ſo low an ebbe, and are ſwolne ſo high that the walls of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary riuers are not able to keepe them within their bankes.</p>
            <p>But (glory be to God) there is no iuſt cauſe why any man ſhould hearken vnto the <hi>ſciſmaticall</hi> voyce of <hi>exite,</hi> or ſeparate from the <hi>Church</hi> of Great <hi>Britaine;</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery article, of whoſe faith is grounded vpon the ſure <hi>rocke Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> and ſubiect to no battery; ſhe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth no other ſupreame head but him, no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rule of <hi>faith</hi> but his <hi>word,</hi> no other <hi>propitiatory ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice</hi> but his <hi>death,</hi> no <hi>purgatory</hi> but his <hi>blood<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> &amp; no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>merit</hi> but his <hi>obedience. Nemo ſuper hoc fundamento aliud ponat quam quod poſitum eſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.11.</note> To this Church doth belong the couenant, the promiſes of <hi>Peace,</hi> of <hi>Loue,</hi> of <hi>Saluation,</hi> of the <hi>preſence of God,</hi> of his <hi>graces, power</hi> &amp;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17407:24"/> 
               <hi>protection.</hi> We haue that Catholike Church which is founded vpon, and agreeth with the trueth of the <hi>Scripture,</hi> that antiquitie which agreeth with the veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>Scripture,</hi> that number which worſhip <hi>God</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rules of the <hi>Scripture,</hi> ſo farre as human infirmity can reach; we haue that ſucceſſion which ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth in the trueth of doctrine deliuered in the <hi>Scripture,</hi> that <hi>vnitie</hi> which beleeues the <hi>trinitie</hi> taught in <hi>Scripture,</hi> &amp; that <hi>viſible</hi> congregation which is ſeene to <hi>God</hi> as he hath reuealed himſelfe in the <hi>Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our ceremonies <hi>virulently</hi> oppoſed by the <hi>ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall</hi> dregs of our owne ſeparatiſts, other braine-ſicke ſectaries, or prophane hypocrites, are few, but <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> many inſtructions, neither burthning the Church with the multitude, or blemiſhing her face with the <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> of externall <hi>rites,</hi> in all which ſhee follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth her doctrine as the beames the <hi>Sunne,</hi> a ſhadow the body, or a line the <hi>Center.</hi> As in our Church the word is truly preached: ſo in euery circumſtance of policie and diſcipline there is no <hi>repugnancie</hi> to that doctrine, or to that decency commanded by the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the whole frame of our externall gouernment <hi>God</hi> hath his true worſhip, <hi>Princes</hi> lawfull obedience, the lawes due reſpect, and <hi>Paſtors</hi> beſeeming reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. All our policy tends to the pure preaching of the word, right adminiſtration of the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> to the lawfull vocation of <hi>Paſtors,</hi> charitable ſupplying of the poore, to the <hi>ſedulous</hi> correction of manners, carefull remouall of ſcandall, and to the cheriſhing of <hi>Chriſtian vnitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:17407:25"/>
            <p>Thus hath our Church all the notes by which ſhee may ſafely walke in this doubtfull way of mortalitie, if ſome <hi>perſonall</hi> infirmities, or abuſe of good Lawes, ſomtimes <hi>eclipſe</hi> the dignity of offendors (as they haue done in the moſt pure <hi>Church</hi> is that euer was, or ſhall be, in the <hi>Church</hi> militant) they are by priuate weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or omiſſion, but not by generall inſtitution and allowance.</p>
            <p>In one word, our Church is euery way happy, if with all other bleſſings, her children may bee conioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in <hi>Feare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.5.</note> 
               <hi>Loue</hi> and <hi>obedience,</hi> as they are in one Lord, in one Faith, and in one Baptiſme, that as the loue of Chriſt combineth them one way; ſo the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints may vnite them another way. For, what <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> can cure that ſtate, wherein euery ſingular ſpirit, factious fondling, or malecontented humoriſt, neither regard the face of <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Councels,</hi> nor their obedience to Lawes: but on the contrary, magnifie nothing but the obortiue births and firy oppoſitions of their fond conceptions; meaſuring all things according to the wilde and gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy apprehenſions of their owne crazy braines, as if the ſole skill of good gouernment had left her publike ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation to dwell retired with ſome few of a partie cullored liuery, ſome of whom doe not bluſh to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade their ouer capable auditors, of ſuch pleaſing er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, that it is the ſpeciall <hi>illuminatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> whereby they diſcerne in the Scripture euery circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of their diſcipline, or other poſition, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers cannot: but ſuch men would doe better, <hi>not to truſt to euery ſpirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. Ioh. 4.1.</note> becauſe there are but two wayes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17407:25"/> the ſpirit leadeth men vnto all truth, the one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary extending it ſelfe but to ſome few, and is now ceaſed; the other common vnto all that are of God.</p>
            <p>The firſt, by a ſpeciall diuine excellency we call <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation,</hi> and the ſecond way is called reaſon. If the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit by <hi>reuelation</hi> hath diſcouered vnto the ſeparatiſts, the ſecrets of their diſcipline, and liberty of their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſh tongues and <hi>lawleſſe</hi> pens,<note place="margin">Tertul. de preſcrip. c. 30.</note> which are the <hi>trumpets</hi> of <hi>ſedition,</hi> diſobedience, malice and ſcandall, they muſt man and wife profeſſe themſelues <hi>Prophets;</hi> or if reaſon led by the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of that ſpirit, they muſt for euery inuectiue, and article which they diſperſe and hold, ſhew ſome reaſon as ſtrong as their <hi>Satirs</hi> are bitter, or their perſwaſion earneſt. It is not the fire of railing, or the <hi>feruency</hi> of perſwaſion, incenſed by malice or paſſion, but the ſoundneſſe of reaſon, which muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare opinions to proceed from the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and not from <hi>fraud</hi> of that ſpirit, who is ſtrong in illuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. They that take vpon them to impugne authority, are to found themſelues, and examine whether they be puft vp with pride, making their imaginations. <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.4.</note> or whether they can proue their vocation as <hi>Moyſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> did, that hee that called them to ſo high a dignitie, may giue them power to approue their vocation, and <hi>induce</hi> the world to honour and reuerence them for their extraordinary workes and <hi>ſupernaturall</hi> vertues.</p>
            <p>But if <hi>Didoclauius,</hi> the <hi>Patriarch</hi> of <hi>Pſeudo-Purita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme,</hi> and other ſeparatiſts of his profeſſion, ſhow not
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17407:26"/> their vocation by other miracles and better reaſon, then by accurſed ſcandall, prophane cenſure, and <hi>ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi> lybels, <hi>quae in verecundae frontis nebulones olent</hi> We muſt not take <hi>Brightmans Apocalipſis, Apocalipſeos,</hi> the altar of <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> and other the like <hi>Chimeraes</hi> of diſtraction or melancholie, and malecontented me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations for warrant. Becauſe all the gifts of Gods ſpirit doe ſo naturally tend to brotherly loue and common peace, that we haue iuſt cauſe to ſuſpect that if ſuch doctrine did proceed from Gods ſpirit, it ſhould bee deliuered in ſober, calme and peaceable manner, according to the inſpiration of Gods ſpirit, and not in bitterneſſe of railing and lybelling.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Melle prius quam felle tentandae ſunt euangelicae cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Other <hi>Simbols</hi> of paſtorall vocation there be, as <hi>perfect zeale, right knoledge, a good conſcience, not to bee railors, contentious,</hi> and <hi>authours of diuiſion, to be pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in perſecution,</hi> louing the <hi>vnitie</hi> of <hi>brotherhood and deputed to death.</hi> If with any part of the former, and this ballance of the ſanctuary, the life, doctrine, and pretended zeal of our Separatiſts agree, let al of ſound iudgement follow or fauour them as they finde cauſe.</p>
            <p>I haue not ſwerued from the trueth in the leaſt cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance thereof; or if I would, the <hi>recent</hi> actions which I oppoſe, will not ſuffer me to belye the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors. If I haue exceeded my intended breuitie, the intricacie of the ſubiect will free mee. If I haue beene conſtrained rudely and diſorderly to heape to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether this diſcourſe in a ſhorter ſcantling, then the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17407:26"/> multiplicitie of aduerſe calumnies require, I hope I ſhall finde a time to ſupply that neceſſitous eſcape. If my rough hewne diſcourſe ſeeme ſomewhat harſh to the delicate eares of ſeparation: Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for me, That againſt <hi>ſchiſmaticall</hi> inſolencie no cenſure can bee too ſtrict, or expoſtulation too ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere.</p>
            <p>If all that I haue ſayd bee conferred with the leaſt impudent <hi>perſonall</hi> aſperſion of thouſands, vomited by thoſe firebrands, whom I haue ſlightly ſhadowed and delineate, my ſtile will proue more ſmooth then ſuch helliſh practiſes deſerue, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon patience allow; and ſo I come to my three-fold aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:17407:27"/>
               <p>FIrſt then to come to you (my Lords) that are <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Rulers</hi> by place in the Church of <hi>Scotland;</hi> I neede not to call to your memorie, that you are the <hi>Sickles,</hi> vnder your Soueraigne, to cut downe euery Weed in the Garden of the Church, the <hi>Snaffles</hi> to bridle <hi>Schiſmes,</hi> and the <hi>Centinels</hi> to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee <hi>ne quid detrimenti Eccleſia patiatur.</hi> You know well, that your Authoritie is to cut off the head of this <hi>Hidra</hi> of <hi>Diuiſion,</hi> which ſpringeth vp with ſuch <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> that your care and vigilancie is, ſo farre as may be, to eaſe his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> of thoſe <hi>Tumults</hi> wherewith he is dayly ſo much infeſted; that you are as well to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend euery <hi>Breach</hi> in the <hi>Walls,</hi> as <hi>Rupture</hi> in the bodie of the <hi>Church;</hi> and that euery eſcape of <hi>Omiſsion</hi> in your places, is no leſſe lyable to <hi>ſcandall,</hi> then faults of <hi>Commiſsion</hi> in your <hi>perſons.</hi> Your <hi>Innocencie</hi> is much wronged by <hi>Didoclauius</hi> and his brethren <hi>Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiſts,</hi> who labour as well by all ſuch ſecret <hi>practiſes,</hi> as by publicke <hi>Satyrs,</hi> at home or abroad may draw your <hi>Authoritie</hi> or <hi>Perſons</hi> into <hi>contempt.</hi> But <hi>my hope</hi> is, that your long patience will call to your conſideration, that the wiſedome of good Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment looketh euer exactly at firſt into the tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe Lawes that are to be obſerued by future Ages, and that <hi>Clergie</hi> and <hi>Learning, Magiſtracie</hi> and <hi>Lawes</hi> are ſo chayned together, that as without <hi>Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> the one cannot be inſtructed, ſo without reſpect
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17407:27"/> to <hi>Lawes, Magiſtracy</hi> walketh without attendance, and is rather a <hi>title</hi> of <hi>honour</hi> then a <hi>frame</hi> of <hi>obedience.</hi> As we doe not more reuerence and adore God in the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious architect of the <hi>world,</hi> then in the wiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of it. So doe wee not more admire Magiſtracie in the compaſſing and compoſing the extent of their gouernment, then in the prudent adminiſtration and preſeruation thereof, from iniuſtice, violence, ſedition, faction and diſſention the <hi>earthquakes</hi> that remoue it from the <hi>Center.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is no poſſible way vnto peace and quietneſſe vnleſſe the probable voyce of euery entire ſocietie or body politike ouer-rule all priuare opinion of that ſame body. <hi>Councels</hi> are to no purpoſe if once their determination ſet downe, men may afterwards de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend publikely their opinions. As theſe things which the law of God leaueth arbitrary, are all ſubiect to the <hi>poſitiue Lawes</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and to be vſed till like au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ſee iuſt &amp; reaſonable cauſe to alter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſo theſe Lawes of the <hi>Church</hi> abridge priuate mens libertie in ſuch things that are not diſſonant from the Lawes of God; if it were not ſo, we ſhould ouerturne the world and make euery man his own commander and Iudge.</p>
               <p>Theſe conſiderations I leaue to your fatherly care, if I haue ſaid too much, or to little purpoſe; it is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I can doe nothing but tattle; but if I were able to do more, I would doe it, that our diuiſions might not be tould in <hi>Gath,</hi> nor our nakedneſſe publiſhed in the ſtreets of <hi>Askelon.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:17407:28"/>
               <p>IN the ſecond place, I come to you of the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or elſewhere within his <hi>Maieſties Dominions,</hi> that are <hi>Lanternes</hi> of direction vnto your followers: To you that thus frame the peoples hearts, and on whoſe ſhoulders lyeth the burthen of this cauſe, which ſo troubleth the common Peace.</p>
               <p>I beſeech you lend me patient hearing to that which in few wordes I ſhall deliuer vnto you from my ſoule, and in the ſinceritie of my heart, and whereof I hope you will iudge more charitable, then to thinke that you reade the wordes of an aduerſarie againſt that Truth which you ſay you profeſſe, but of one that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth to embrace the ſame Truth with you, if it bee Truth. Although I be not of the Tribe of <hi>Leui,</hi> yet am I of the Tents of <hi>Sem:</hi> Regard not then who it is that ſpeaketh, but weigh the truth of what I ſhall ſpeake.</p>
               <p>Firſt, if without fore-ſtalled or preiudicate affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you will truely examine that ſame externall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment eſtabliſhed (which you oppoſe) you ſhall finde it ſuch, as neither the Law of God or man, hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto alleadged, are of ſufficient force to diſprooue your obedience thereunto: but on the contrarie, that the Frame of that Gouernment which you maintaine is inſufficient to eſtabliſh any well affected Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſo long as it oppoſeth the current of lawfull Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie: Neither in all your impartiall enquirie ſhall you finde one cleare proofe whereby it may bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, that your Oppoſition is not by miſ-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception and error named the Ordinance of IESVS CHRIST.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:17407:28"/>
               <p>Though you much vrge <hi>Apoſtolicall</hi> imitation, yet my hope is, that there is none ſo obſtinate amongſt you, but will confeſſe, that many things of the ſame nature were harmeleſſe in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> times, which now would prooue impoſſible, or <hi>ſcandalous;</hi> as the adminiſtration of the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> after ſupper, waſhing of feet, <hi>oſcula ſancta,</hi> the <hi>communitie of goods, the feaſts of charitie, manuall exerciſe,</hi> and the like; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſome, many yeares after were retained in the Church, and now vpon good conſiderations, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued, and other things eſtabliſhed, which the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times could not haue, and are more fit for the Church of Chriſt, then if for conformities ſake to thoſe times, they ſhould be taken away. Or if a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitous imitation of <hi>Apoſtolicall</hi> times, ſhould be yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the externall gouernment of the <hi>Church,</hi> all the <hi>paſsionate exhalations</hi> of <hi>Didoclauius,</hi> and the like di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbers of <hi>State</hi> combined with your beſt reaſons, will neuer be able to proue that your compleat form of diſcipline, was wholly practiſed in any age but in this, which for <hi>inſolencie</hi> and <hi>contempt</hi> may bee called the worſt, or that it is otherwiſe warranted but by maruellous poore coniectures and wreſting of <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> to <hi>ſingular opinions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore giue me leaue to intreate you by that <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie</hi> which is the <hi>crowne</hi> of well <hi>affected Chriſtian minds,</hi> by the obligation which you owe vnto the peace of the <hi>Church,</hi> by the care of your owne <hi>ſoules</hi> and ſaluation of Gods people committed to your charge, that (beſide many other important conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations) you will lay before you the neceſſitie of vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:17407:29"/> and <hi>inteſtine</hi> tranquillitie at this time, when now or neuer your allegeance challengeth your loyalty and vnited forces.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Animos veſtros commune iungat periculum, ſimultas poſt ſit, ne tum denique veſtra intelligatis bona, cum quae in poteſtate habetis ea amiſeritis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Meditate deepely with your beſt recollected ſences, that if his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> ſhould now cheriſh in his owne boſome the leaſt Coale of <hi>home-bred Sedition,</hi> that might obviate the ſucceſſefull iſſue of his iuſt and <hi>holy deſignes,</hi> the World might iuſtly take notice, that his Royall prouidence is farre ſhort of that care which ſo long hath vpholden the moſt peaceable Gouernment that any Age can <hi>paralell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Call to minde, that as God hath giuen him a wiſe and vnderſtanding heart, to iudge betwixt <hi>good</hi> and <hi>euill,</hi> ſo hath he giuen him a ſtrong Arme, to caſt out from his people <hi>euery root that bringeth</hi> forth <hi>Worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> and <hi>Gall.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. Mirror of holy Warre, dedicated to the high Court of Parliament of England.</note> He needeth not a <hi>Speculum belli ſacri,</hi> or a Looking <hi>Bable,</hi> to informe him, that the open ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of <hi>State</hi> are quickly diſcouered; but the <hi>Mothes, Cancers, vlcerous ſores,</hi> and <hi>Hecticks</hi> ariſing from <hi>ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi> ſubiects, are ſeldome ſeene till they be paſt cure, and become the ſpoyle of State, and opprobrie of <hi>Stateſ-men.</hi> Neither is hee ignorant, that whatſoeuer ſubiect repineth againſt iuſt <hi>Lawes,</hi> or incroacheth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Regalities</hi> of the King, either ſeeketh to weare his Crowne, commaund it, or to diſclayme his alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance.</p>
               <p>Thinke not then, that a King ſo religiouſly wiſe, for ſatisfaction of fond iealouſies (which hee hath further
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:17407:29"/> ſecured then modeſtie or reaſon could haue entreated, farre leſſe importuned) will re-eſtabliſh a confuſed <hi>Anarchie,</hi> or giue way that an <hi>Oligarchie</hi> of Elders, compoſed for the moſt part of <hi>ignorant</hi> and <hi>mutinous</hi> members, ſhall be the <hi>Lesbian Rule,</hi> to <hi>ſquare, iudge, direct, gouerne,</hi> and be the <hi>Dictator</hi> of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> at home and abroad. As his <hi>Maieſties</hi> long experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hath taught him, that ſuch tumultuous <hi>Councels</hi> of orderleſſe <hi>paritie</hi> are the diſ-tuned ſtrings that mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the <hi>Harmonie</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and diſturbe the qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et of the <hi>State;</hi> ſo in thankefull acknowledgement, that God hath beene ſo <hi>propitious</hi> vnto him, in giuing him an <hi>vnderſtanding heart,</hi> endued with <hi>prouidence, prudence, moderation,</hi> and <hi>goodneſſe,</hi> whereby hee hath happily diuerted and diſperſed all <hi>maleuolent aſpects</hi> of <hi>diſaſterous ſtarres,</hi> which haue threatened the leaſt eclipſe of the <hi>ſunne-ſhine</hi> of thoſe peaceable dayes which wee haue ſo long poſſeſſed, hee can doe no leſſe then continue his former care, and prouide for the ſafetie and bodie of his <hi>Empire,</hi> that euery good ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect may ſleepe in his Watchings, and reſt in his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
               <p>Adde to theſe Conſiderations, that his <hi>Maieſties</hi> white <hi>Colours</hi> haue long attended your <hi>ſubmiſsion</hi> at the Gates of your <hi>Rebellion;</hi> if his <hi>approaches</hi> draw neerer, who knoweth what may follow? An aduiſed <hi>Fabius</hi> is no leſſe to be feared then a fighting <hi>Marcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus.</hi> True <hi>wiſdome</hi> knoweth as well how to <hi>ſacrifice</hi> at the <hi>Altar</hi> of <hi>Mars,</hi> as to offer in the <hi>Temple</hi> of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerua,</hi> and is no leſſe ſeene in the <hi>Myſteries</hi> of Warre, then in the <hi>Councels</hi> of Peace. Sometimes the day
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17407:30"/> that beginneth with <hi>Sunne-ſhine,</hi> endeth with <hi>Stormes,</hi> and ſome who now refuſe to ſing <hi>Gloria Patri,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Some of this pure profeſſion hath bin lately ſo mad, as to impugne that Gloria Patri ſhould bee read in the Church Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie, or ſung after the Pſalms</note> perhaps hereafter may be taught a Leſſon of obedience, <hi>Sicut erat in principio.</hi> You cannot iuſtly complaine, but that <hi>patience</hi> hath beene admirable, which hath giuen way to thoſe violent Spirits, whoſe <hi>actions</hi> now ſhew, that without pulling of them vpon their knees, they can be hardly reduced to order: but if others be wiſe, they may make good vſe of ſuch madneſſe.</p>
               <q>Optimum conſilium aliena frui inſania.</q>
               <p>It is bad policie to let danger knocke at the doore, and it is a worthie ſaying beſeeming a <hi>Stateſ-man,</hi> That ſolid and grounded courſes which keepe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers aloofe,<note place="margin">L. Verul.</note> are better then fine ſhifts and deliueries, when they are neere.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Damb. in cauſ. Crim. Dec. lib. 7. Farin. Bod. de repub. Iac. 1. parl. 2. c 43. Iac. 5. parl. 6. c. 83. Iac. 6. Parl. 8. c. 134. Parl 10. c. 10. Parl. Parl. 14. c. 259. Ed. 1. an. 3. c. 25. Hen. 8. an. 37. c. 10. Phil. and Mar. an. c 3. Eliz. an 8. c. 7.</note>I will not act the Ciuilian, in reſoluing whether or not Conſpiracies, entertainment of intelligence for Faction, priuate Conuenticles inciting Commotion, or the abaters and <hi>Miniſters</hi> of inſtruction to treaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable attempts, be within the compaſſe of Treaſon; becauſe it is euident by our auncient and moderne Municipall Lawes, which are, or ought to be the bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles to breake and curbe vnruly <hi>Colts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a friendly intereſt might haue place, I could wiſh, that ſuch of you as know the danger to which you are lyable, ſhould appeale to a Pardon in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, by tendering your obedience to conformitie, whileſt you haue time, and not to ſtand to a tryall in <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> when perhaps it will be too late for thoſe <hi>Royall Offers</hi> and <hi>Remonſtrances,</hi> ſo oft reiected, to yeeld to thoſe <hi>Metaphyſicall repining Spirits,</hi> who can
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:17407:30"/> diſcerne the face of the skie, but cannot diſcerne the difference of times, or their owne danger, when de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction like <hi>Damocles</hi> ſword hangeth perpendiculer ouer their heads.</p>
               <p>It is obiected by <hi>Demades</hi> againſt the <hi>Athenians,</hi> that they neuer intreated for peace, but in mourning gownes, that is after great calamitie in warre. After wit is oft times bought at a deere rate by the diſloyall children of pride, <hi>ſingularitie</hi> and <hi>diſobedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In nobis id verum quibus hoſtis in latere, &amp; non tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ad Portas Hanniball, &amp; tamen dulci fortuna litiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It cannot bee expeſſed how much it greeueth the heart of euery ſober Chriſtian, that <hi>ſoueraigntie, Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy,</hi> and things of ſpeciall <hi>excellency</hi> ſhould be thus bitten at by men ouerflowing with peace, whom God hath endued with graces of wit and learning to bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter purpoſes, and that gentle admonitions which ought to reforme them, doe but encreaſe their obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy, and are occaſions of labouring more earneſtly to entangle vnwary minds in the ſnares of their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Gens hominum fertur rapidis obuia fatis.</l>
                  <l>Incerta ſui, ſtigiaſque vltro querimus vndas.</l>
               </q>
               <p>There is none ſo ignorant amongſt you, bur know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>vos eſtis dii,</hi> is a prerogatiue or <hi>ſummum imperium</hi> giuen to <hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>eſtote ſubditi,</hi> a command of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, telling ſubiects, that as the hand muſt wither that toucheth: <hi>ſo the tongue muſt fall out that taxeth the Lords annoynted againſt whom the very Angels of heauen giue not railing iudgement before the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:17407:31"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. Iud. 1.9.</note>
                  <hi>When Michael the Archangell deſputed with Sathan the Prince of darkeneſſe about the body of</hi> Moſes; hee durſt not blame him with curſed ſpeaking, but ſayd <hi>increpet te dominus, the Lord rebuke thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the old Teſtament Kings were directly gouernours euer the Church; they did purge corruption, reforme abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, brought the Arke to her place, builded the Temple, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated the ſame,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 6. 1. Reg. 16.3.8.</note> 
                  <hi>and renued the couenant betwixt God and the people.</hi> To theſe actions their titles giuen by the Almighty are ſutable; <hi>They are called the ſonnes of the moſt high,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 49.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Gods, Angels of God, nurſing Fathers of the Church, and the Lights of Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 1.3. Rom. 13.1.2.3.4.5. 2. Pet. 13.14. Mat. 22.21.</note>
                  <hi>In the new Teſtament, obedience to Princes is euery where inioyned, and euery ſoule commanded to be ſubiect to them for conſcience ſake;</hi> in the whole booke of God they are <hi>vindices vtriuſque tabulae,</hi> by commanding due obedience to be giuen to Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeements, and in giuing life to the ordinances of the Church by their ciuill ſword.<note place="margin">Auguſt. Epiſt. contra Donat.</note> Both diuine and human lawes enable <hi>Princes</hi> to preuent confuſion of opinions and <hi>ſciſmes</hi> that infect the world with <hi>Atheiſme,</hi> and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadow the face of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> ſimplicitie with ſelfe-conceit,<note place="margin">Tim. 6.20.</note> ſchoole ſubtleties, vaine babling, and oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſcience falſly ſo called.</p>
               <p>It is a fond arrogant preſumption to intrude euery ſingular conception vpon the Church, by railing and malitious aſperſions, and not by modeſty and reaſon, by which only diuine trueth will iſſue and be brought to light. All contrary factious practiſes, tumultuary motions, and <hi>virulent</hi> inuectiues, haue euer been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned as arch policies to <hi>animate ſedition,</hi> and giue
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:17407:31"/> the <hi>vulgar people</hi> heartning to make God the authour of rebellion, and themſelues his deputies in the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</p>
               <p>This aſſumed liberty dayly beaten in <hi>popular eares</hi> is onely a <hi>Circean ſong,</hi> rather beſeeming the <hi>hoords</hi> of <hi>Tartarians,</hi> then commonwealth of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> a <hi>para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxe</hi> in which all <hi>Princes</hi> haue intereſt, and an <hi>inſolency</hi> incredible to poſteritie, if euery <hi>Ariſtarchus</hi> may cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, euery <hi>Gracchus</hi> giue ſentence, or euery ſubiect ſit in iudgement againſt <hi>ſoueraigntie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They are bad <hi>Stateſ-men</hi> that vniuſtly take from the ſubiect to add to the <hi>prerogatiues</hi> or <hi>reuenues</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi> thereby they weaken <hi>ſoueraigntie,</hi> depriue it of the loue of the people, make the life of it troubleſome and ſubiect to diſeaſes: but you like worſe <hi>Stateſmen,</hi> touch the ſtring of <hi>ſoueraignty</hi> with too rough a hand, or rather breake it in pulling the natural feathers from it, to enlarge <hi>popular</hi> libertie.</p>
               <p>In aduancing this <hi>Anarchy,</hi> you open a dore to all manner of euils, which with licentiouſneſſe and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience ruſh into the commonwealth and make the great <hi>frame</hi> of <hi>ſoueraigne Empire</hi> vnproportionable, vncomely, and altogether vnſeruiceable, either for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of vice, aduancement of vertue, or for vniting of inward power againſt forraine force, which are the main ends of <hi>royall inſtitution.</hi> The large and ſure point of <hi>mediocrity</hi> is loſt in the narrow compaſſe of your <hi>ſingularitie,</hi> wherein few or none haue euer found it; for, if affaires bee not euenly ballanced without ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to extreames, <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State gouernment</hi> may
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:17407:32"/> erre vpon either hand, and ſo fall into an <hi>anarchy</hi> or <hi>tyranny.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Fata ſi liceret mihi</l>
                  <l>Fingere arbitrio meo</l>
                  <l>Temperem Zephiro leui</l>
                  <l>Vela, ne preſſae graui</l>
                  <l>Strepitu antennae tremant</l>
                  <l>Tuta me media vehat</l>
                  <l>Vita decurrens via.</l>
                  <l>Quicquid exceſsit modum</l>
                  <l>Pendet inſtabili loco.</l>
               </q>
               <p>As <hi>wiſdome</hi> is the <hi>ſacred</hi> worker of all things: ſo is a modeſt <hi>carriage</hi> one of her chiefeſt effects, arming the poſſeſſors with a wel compoſed orderly modeſtie, as well to encounter the ſecret <hi>Ambuſcados,</hi> as open aſſaults of <hi>aduerſe accidents.</hi> Neither doth <hi>wiſdome</hi> floriſh in any thing more then in the <hi>religious mutuall chaſt amplexures</hi> wherewith <hi>order, vnitie</hi> and <hi>loue</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace one another, perfuming <hi>heauen</hi> and <hi>earth</hi> with a <hi>delicious fragrancy,</hi> which <hi>ſhineth</hi> like a <hi>reſplendent light</hi> in the <hi>firmament</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> and common wealth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hieron. ad Damaſc.</note>
                  <hi>Si quis in hac arca non fuerit, peribit, regnante dilu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uio; ſi quis extra hanc domum agnum commederit propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſweetneſſe of <hi>Muſicke</hi> hath maſtered mens fierceſt affections, and it is wittily <hi>emblem'd,</hi> that <hi>har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi> cauſed the ſtones of <hi>Thebes</hi> ioyne themſelues in vniforme proportion of building.</p>
               <p>If you picture or preſent to your ſelues, the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent bleſſings that will acrue to the cauſe of <hi>religion</hi> by the <hi>vnanimous ioynture</hi> of all true profeſſors, certainly you ſhall at once in the ſame meaſure graue in your
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:17407:32"/> hearts a <hi>religious reuerent reſpect</hi> towards that ſacred bond of <hi>vnity</hi> and <hi>loue,</hi> ſo much diſtracted by paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate <hi>diſtempers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is nothing more contrary to religion, then that orderleſſe <hi>anarchy, ſedition, calumny, ſtrife, enuy,</hi> &amp; <hi>malice,</hi> the <hi>rebels</hi> of heauen incenſed by <hi>contention,</hi> ſhould be entertaind as moſt welcome gueſts to thoſe who aſſume the ſole title of purity. But if you wil haue the world to be the <hi>Theater</hi> of your <hi>praiſes,</hi> or dignifie your deſert with ſo <hi>glorious titles,</hi> conſort your <hi>loue, charitie, wiſdome</hi> and peaceable <hi>conuerſation,</hi> with thoſe attributes wherewith now your actions ſhow you but hood-winke the world.</p>
               <p>In your long digging the barren deſolate and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull quarry of <hi>diſſention,</hi> you haue gotten nothing but vnſeruiceable <hi>ſtones</hi> for the <hi>ſanctuary,</hi> and <hi>rubbidge</hi> of <hi>ſcandall</hi> for your ſelues: but from the rich <hi>mines</hi> of <hi>obedience, peace</hi> &amp; chriſtian <hi>ſociety,</hi> you ſhall reap a <hi>gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den harueſt</hi> of thoſe <hi>fruits</hi> of our <hi>faith,</hi> which are onely able to direct vs towards <hi>heauenly Ieruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O! then cal your actions to a reckoning, examine the cauſe you haue taken in hand, laying aſide that bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>gal</hi> wherewith hitherto you haue ouer-aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and with meekneſſe ſearching the trueth.</p>
               <p>Thinke you are men and may erre. Sift impartially your owne hearts, whether it be force of reaſon, or <hi>vehemency</hi> of <hi>paſsion</hi> that feedeth your opinions.</p>
               <p>When you diſcouer the <hi>trueth,</hi> ſeeke not to couer it with gloſing <hi>deluſions,</hi> but acknowledge the greatnes thereof, and thinke it your greateſt victory when the ſame ouerruleth you.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:17407:33"/>
               <p>Deceiue not your ſelues, by thinking, that ſtaying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> our owne Countrey you may as well ſhake off your alleageance, farre leſſe inueſt your ſelues in <hi>ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Power</hi> (which is a Note aboue <hi>Ela,</hi> ſet to the Tune of <hi>Iohn Knox, Geneuating</hi> in a wrong <hi>Diapaſon</hi>) as ſome by running to <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> make themſelues <hi>Libertinos</hi> and <hi>Ciues alienae Reipublicae,</hi> to their ſhame.</p>
               <p>If others <hi>Separatiſts</hi> will follow their Sent, or if perhaps their further contempt procure them a <hi>Mitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> or <hi>ſafe-conduct</hi> thither, certainely the <hi>Church</hi> will be eaſed, and the <hi>State</hi> disburthened of thoſe vnquiet Spirits, whoſe enſuing miſerie will make them <hi>ſenſible</hi> of their vnaduiſed choyſe, in leauing Gods people committed to their charge, and in proſtituting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues (againſt eyther conſcience, or wiſdome) to bee ſlaues, at leaſt conſorts, to the impure Luſts of <hi>Iuda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme,</hi> Sectaries, or <hi>Schiſme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neyther is it to be feared, that the <hi>Nurſeries</hi> and Schooles of Learning in Great <hi>Brittaine</hi> are ſo barren (as <hi>Didoclauius</hi> impudently vpbraideth them) that they cannot ſupply the <hi>Miniſterie</hi> with <hi>Paſtors</hi> euery way as able, and in the point of conformitie to Gods Ordinances, more fit to be Labourers in the <hi>Lords Harueſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In your ordinarie diſcourſe, and in that <hi>poyſonable Libell,</hi> falſely entituled, <hi>The Speech of the Kirke of Scotland,</hi> you deſire to haue a hearing; that by reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, matters in queſtion may be determined, and that the Lawes alreadie made may ſleepe, and haue no power ouer you, till publikely you eyther confeſſe
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:17407:33"/> your error (which is <hi>Aethiopem lauare</hi>) or by ſound rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon draw others to your opinion.</p>
               <p>If it might pleaſe his <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> vpon whoſe appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation the matter dependeth, to <hi>condiſcend</hi> ſo farre, the cauſe of the <hi>Church</hi> maintained is ſuch, that it nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not to ſhun any triall but rather appealeth to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>ſolemne</hi> conference, where in quiet orderly ſort, reaſon and not confuſed voyces of preiudicat opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons might haue place.</p>
               <p>But certainly, according to the reach of my ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der iudgement, your deſire in this, is, but a gliſtring ſhew to dazle <hi>poreblind eyes,</hi> and altogether <hi>diſſonant</hi> from reaſon, that (laying aſide the <hi>concourſe</hi> of deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded minds in thoſe aſſemblyes, which hitherto haue beene found fruitleſſe) lawes once eſtabliſhed, which ought to exact obedience and conſtraint thereunto, ſhould ſo farre ſtoope from taking effect vpon you, till ſome <hi>diſputant</hi> can perſwade you to conformity; or that publike edicts receiued ſhould ceaſe to bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted, in caſe this or that priuate perſon, led by ſome probable conceit ſhould make proteſtation againſt them.</p>
               <p>There was neuer yet any thing ſo agreeable to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which hath beene free of oppoſition: for this cauſe it is a maine end why <hi>Counels</hi> are aſſembled, that by ſentence of iudgement they may determine thoſe ſtrifes that <hi>diſputes</hi> can hardly doe: our nature is ſoe loaden with wilfulneſſe and ſelfe conceit, that there is ſmall hope, matters of this quality will haue any quiet end, vnleſſe <hi>definitiue determinations</hi> giuen, may ſtand and enforce a neceſſitie of ſilence thereafter.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:17407:34"/>
               <p>Your owne <hi>Patriarch Didoclauius</hi> telleth you, that by royall permiſſion you haue celebrated moe <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels</hi> in 60. then hath bin in England theſe 300. yeeres.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In Eccleſia Scoticana vbi nulli erant Epiſcopi aut Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolotani plura Concilia Nationalia à prima reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione celebrata ſunt quam hos annos</hi> 300. <hi>in Anglia pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincialia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Altar. Damſc. pag. 58.</note> 
                  <hi>vbi Archiepiſcoporum longam &amp; in erruptam ſeriem iactitant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What hath beene the fruit of all thoſe Councels, I haue alreadie told you, and euery weather-beaten Sehpheard can tel you that they were either the <hi>Vſhers</hi> to ſtormes, or the Stage whereon they were acted?</p>
               <p>What hath beene his <hi>Maieſties</hi> pious indeuours in thoſe aſſemblies for remouing many needleſſe queſtions amongſt you, wherewith publike peace hath beene diſturbed, none knoweth better then your ſelues; or with what baſe ingratitude his royall fauors hath beene repaied, (to inſtance one for all) the inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent practices of ſome of you ſince his laſt beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, for your competent maintenance, will witneſſe. Yet doth his <hi>inuincible</hi> clemency (a thing admirable to humane eyes) continue rather willing to regaine you, then to make you the ſubiect of his iuſtice.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Magni ſcilicet animi eſt iniurias in ſumma poteſtate pati.</l>
                  <l>Nec quicquam glorioſius Principe impune leſo.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Since <hi>Heauen, Earth,</hi> your owne <hi>Soules,</hi> the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of your friends, &amp; the fruits of your labours beare witneſſe againſt you, here is no reaſon but that ſame authoritie which you vſurpe, may be maintained by the ouerthrow of ſuch as by further contempt conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:17407:34"/> inſenſible of dutie or fauour. Men ſeldome kicke at prickes without harme, or dance in Nets not ſeene, your proiects run <hi>byas,</hi> your policies are diſcouered, your <hi>Machinations</hi> are layed open, and for ought that can be ſeene, nothing reſteth but expectation of your ſpeedy amendment, or of <hi>condigne chaſtiſement</hi> for of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences of ſo high <hi>qualitie. Rebellio in Principes conatu irrito imperia ſemper promouet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If theſe conſiderations may moue you, it will bee a great ioy to me, and farre greater benefit to you; no leſſe in regard of your <hi>ſpirituall</hi> then <hi>temporall</hi> condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; if it happen otherwiſe, remember that I haue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged my conſcience in ſo hard and ſtiffe-nected an age, wherein <hi>Pride, Singularitie</hi> and <hi>Contention</hi> rage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Humilitie, Vnitie</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian Societie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The neerer things come to their <hi>Center,</hi> they moue the faſter; the neerer the <hi>Sun</hi> approcheth the <hi>Zenith,</hi> it is the hotter, and when lewd <hi>miſdemeanours</hi> are at full height oppoſed againſt <hi>Vertue,</hi> an <hi>eclipſe</hi> or totall <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion</hi> muſt follow.</p>
               <p>LAſtly, as a feeling Member of common Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, I arriue at the <hi>Hauen</hi> of all good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ects, at whoſe Gates the <hi>Contagion</hi> of <hi>Schiſme</hi> hath not yet ſought ſhelter, as well in all dutifull af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection <hi>congratulating</hi> your by-paſt conſtancie, as ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciting your wonted obedience to <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerents. Gods</hi> manifold bleſſings inuite you to the one, the long peace which you haue enioyed, enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth you to the other, and the remembrance of both, challenge on your part thankefull hearts, modeſt
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:17407:35"/> tongues, and reciprocall obligation for ſo high bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding fauors.</p>
               <p>If you will follow the light of ſound ſincere iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without <hi>cloud</hi> of preiudice or miſt of paſſionate affection; remember that the bonds of Chriſtian vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie are ſo to be maintained, that the bonds of humane ſocietie be not diſſolued.</p>
               <p>If you will winde vp all your Ends vpon this Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, follow not ſuch Guides as lead you from <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> to <hi>Samaria,</hi> from the <hi>Mountaine</hi> of <hi>God</hi> to the <hi>Valley</hi> of <hi>Benhinnon;</hi> neyther affect ſuch <hi>Quackſaluers</hi> as inflame your wounds with bitter waters of <hi>Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bahe,</hi> when they ſhould annoynt them with ſweete balmes of <hi>Gilead:</hi> Make a concord of diſcords, an vnion of diuiſion, and contend religiouſly for good life, peaceable conuerſation; and by excellencie of Learning, who ſhall doe moſt good in Church and Commonwealth.</p>
               <p>Let true humilitie kindle heauenly zealous ſparkes of <hi>Loue</hi> in your hearts, to the encreaſe of <hi>Vertue,</hi> that the higheſt reach of your <hi>ambition</hi> may be to glorie in your ſeruice to <hi>God,</hi> and to be eſteemed good ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects to the <hi>King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lay you <hi>Prayers, Humilitie,</hi> and <hi>Patience</hi> vpon the <hi>Altars</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> againſt <hi>Curſing, Pride,</hi> and <hi>Furie;</hi> and on whom he ſendeth the true fire of <hi>zeale,</hi> to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of <hi>ſinne,</hi> let that be receiued.</p>
               <p>Suffer not the ſeameleſſe Coat of your <hi>Sauiour</hi> to be any more cut in pieces; <hi>Vnitie and diſcord will not abide in Noahs Arke, and Chriſt will not be diuided.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let all bitterneſſe and anger, and wrath, crying and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:17407:35"/> euill ſpeaking be put away from you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1.</note> 
                  <hi>with all maliciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That you may be pure, blameleſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 2.15.</note> 
                  <hi>and the ſonnes of God, in the middeſt of a naughtie and crooked Nation, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom you ſhine as Lights in the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But if you haue bitter enuying and ſtrife in your hearts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 3.14.</note> 
                  <hi>reioyce not, neither be lyars againſt the truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This wiſdome deſcendeth not from aboue but is earthly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>ſenſuall, and deuilliſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For where enuie and ſtrife is,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>there is ſedition and all manner of euill workes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Be not ſtumbling blockes to your friends, nor <hi>Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phies</hi> of <hi>Triumph</hi> to your enemies or like Water-men looking forward, but rowing backward.</p>
               <p>Doe not curiouſly prie into the Myſteries and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bale of Princes, which are ſo vnſearchable, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out touch of diſloyaltie or admiſſion they are not to be approched by ſubiects in whom it is contemptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous looſeneſſe to be more apt to cenſure things that are beſt done, then willing to vnderſtand the reaſons why they are done.</p>
               <p>Aſpire not with <hi>Adam</hi> to eate forbidden fruit, in giuing hearing to ſuch <hi>Serpents</hi> as pleade religious ſhowes, but are farre from Religion in their hearts:<note place="margin">Geneſ. 3.6.</note> but looke rather what you ſhould doe, then be readie to <hi>applaud</hi> the faire colours of foule Errors, or the gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering ſhowes of ſuch whited <hi>Tombes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 23.27.</note> on whoſe fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſpeece thinke you ſee written,
<q>
                     <l>—Pulchra lauerna</l>
                     <l>Da mihi fallere ſanctumque videri,</l>
                     <l>Noctem peccatis &amp; fraudibus obtice nubem.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:17407:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:17407:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:17407:37"/>
               <p>If your ſtudie be thus to <hi>Vnitie, Loue Charitie, Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie,</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> your <hi>Glorie</hi> ſhall <hi>ſhine</hi> in your <hi>Faith,</hi> your <hi>Faith</hi> ſhew in your <hi>Workes,</hi> and <hi>Mercie and Truth ſhall meet in your liues:</hi> ſo ſhall your ſtrength neyther conſiſt in the diſ-ioynted <hi>Bones</hi> of <hi>Diſloyaltie,</hi> or in the ſtrengthleſſe <hi>ſinewes</hi> of <hi>Schiſme, Diſobedience,</hi> and arrogant <hi>Preſumption,</hi> the rootes of auncient and preſent <hi>Diſtempers;</hi> but in the ſtrong <hi>Arme</hi> of your dutifull <hi>allegeance</hi> and humble ſubmiſſion to the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of that great <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> who in his owne time, to his <hi>Glorie,</hi> your comfort, and terror of all contrarie <hi>Power,</hi> will vnite euery member of his <hi>glorious Bodie,</hi> or in the ouerthrow of <hi>Korah</hi> waſh away euery <hi>Spot</hi> in your <hi>Garment, diſsipate</hi> euery <hi>Cloud</hi> that obſcureth your <hi>Light, eradicate</hi> euery fruitleſſe <hi>Tree</hi> in your <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> calme the raging <hi>Waues</hi> of foaming <hi>Seas</hi> and <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuous Winds,</hi> that with-hold you from your <hi>Hauen,</hi> and ſo fixe euery wandring <hi>Starre</hi> in your <hi>Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon,</hi> that eyther in <hi>Mercie</hi> or <hi>Iuſtice</hi> his great Name may be glorified, the vnitie of the Church may flouriſh, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to ſupreame Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers encreaſe.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:17407:37"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
